<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dark lantern containing a dim discoverie, in riddles, parables, and semi-riddles, intermixt with cautions, remembrances and predictions, as they were promiscuously and immethodically represented to their author, in his solitary musings, the third of November 1652. about midnight. Whereunto is annexed, a poem, concerning a perpetuall parliament. By Geo. Wither Esquire.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1432_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863797</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 183:E1432[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dark lantern containing a dim discoverie, in riddles, parables, and semi-riddles, intermixt with cautions, remembrances and predictions, as they were promiscuously and immethodically represented to their author, in his solitary musings, the third of November 1652. about midnight. Whereunto is annexed, a poem, concerning a perpetuall parliament. By Geo. Wither Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Austin, and are to be sold by Richard Lowndes at the white Lion in Paul's Church-yard, neer the little north door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116012:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The dark Lantern, Containing A dim Diſcoverie, in Riddles, Parables, and Semi-Riddles, intermixt with Cautions, Remembrances and Predictions, as they were promiſcuouſly and immethodically repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to their <hi>Author,</hi> in his <hi>Solitary Muſings,</hi> the third of <hi>November</hi> 1652. about <hi>Midnight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed, A POEM, Concerning A Perpetuall Parliament.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Geo. Wither</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Auſtin,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Lowndes</hi> at the white Lion in PAUL'S Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, neer the little North Door. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116012:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116012:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THeſe <hi>Poems</hi> were delivered forth to be publiſhed about three moneths paſt, with an expectation that they ſhould have been imprinted forthwith, and had either an accidentall or a negligent delay prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their publication the laſt Term; and perhaps (I being abſent) they were afterward purpoſely delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they might come forth at the beginning of this <hi>Eaſter Term,</hi> by their deſign, who more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Bookſellers advantage, then how much the haſtning of them might concern the publike; by which means it was not finiſhed, untill that very day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> had an unlooked for period: and yet peradventure, in regard of the many timely <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>Remembrances,</hi> which have been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſpiſed, or neglected, <hi>Providence</hi> hath permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe to be delayed, untill their publication came too late, for effecting that which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>Howſoever it will be uſefull to ſome other ends; at leaſt to teſtifie to the world, that what is now come to paſſe, was foreſeen, and endeavours uſed for prevention thereof, which might probably have had good ſucceſſe, if contempt of many forewarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings had not hindred the ſame, it may be, to make way for the accompliſhment of ſomewhat, fore-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in my <hi>Britains Genius;</hi> in which <hi>Poem,</hi> I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured as much in vain to reduce the late <hi>King,</hi> to make uſe of that means which would have effected his
<pb facs="tcp:116012:3"/>
               <hi>reſtoration,</hi> as I have hereby done to preſerve the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> and I heartily beſeech Almighty God, that I may not have occaſion to be as fatall a <hi>Remembrancer</hi> to them who are now in <hi>Throne;</hi> leſt worſe things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to them, then to their Predeceſſors, which I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured will follow, if their proceedings (which I yet ſuſpect not) be not really deſign'd, and made anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their fair pretendings. There are many faults eſcaped in the printing, by reaſon of my abſence, and a Copy haſtily, and not very plainly written, ſome of which are here corrected, the reſt I leave to be amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as you find them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>PAge 5. line 25. for <hi>corall</hi> read <hi>carnall.</hi> p. 32. l. 9 r. Then ſuch as Innocencies cauſe, &amp;c. p. 49. l. 29. r. <hi>Aegypts</hi> thrall. p. 72. l. 13. for <hi>foot</hi> r. <hi>fork.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_Parliament_and_the_people_of_England">
            <pb facs="tcp:116012:3"/>
            <head>TO THE PARLIAMENT, AND PEOPLE OF THE Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SO let me ſpeed, in all that I purſue,</l>
               <l>As, in what <hi>followes,</hi> I mean well to you:</l>
               <l>And, as I bear a loving faithfull <hi>heart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To all of <hi>you, united</hi> and <hi>apart;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Although, I peradventure, may appear</l>
               <l>On ſome <hi>occaſions,</hi> bitterly ſevere,</l>
               <l>To thoſe, in whom, I <hi>private-failings</hi> ſee,</l>
               <l>Which, to the <hi>Publike</hi> may obnoxious be;</l>
               <l>To make them <hi>judge themſelves,</hi> and ſcape the <hi>doom,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which, from another <hi>judgement,</hi> els may come:</l>
               <l>For, at no <hi>ſingle perſon,</hi> have I ſtrook,</l>
               <l>By any <hi>line,</hi> or <hi>paſſage,</hi> in this <hi>book.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If here, I further ſeem to have preſum'd,</l>
               <l>Or, more upon my ſelf to have aſſum'd,</l>
               <l>Then may be <hi>warrantable</hi> thought, at firſt,</l>
               <l>Examine it, before you judge the worſt;</l>
               <l>And, try by <hi>circumſtances</hi> (as ye may)</l>
               <l>What <hi>Spirit,</hi> hath directed me this way;</l>
               <l>Or, for what likely <hi>ends,</hi> or for whoſe <hi>ſake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I could, or dared, this <hi>attempt</hi> to make;</l>
               <l>Except it were for GODS, for <hi>your,</hi> and <hi>mine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As they with one another, do intwine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:116012:4"/>
               <l>Yea, ſearch, if my <hi>Religion, ſtudies, wayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or, <hi>manners</hi> (which have beene throughout my dayes,</l>
               <l>Before your eyes) may any <hi>ſign</hi> afford,</l>
               <l>That, I have, hitherto, in <hi>deed,</hi> or <hi>word,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Been an <hi>Impoſtor;</hi> or, preſented you</l>
               <l>With ought, that hath been <hi>uſeleſſe,</hi> or <hi>untrue;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as that juſtly may incline your mind,</l>
               <l>Let theſe <hi>expreſſions</hi> acceptation find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If <hi>madneſſe,</hi> they appear; conſider well,</l>
               <l>That, ſuch <hi>miſcenſurings</hi> have often fell</l>
               <l>On <hi>ſober men,</hi> when thoſe deluding crimes,</l>
               <l>Were prevalent, which raign in theſe our times.</l>
               <l>If <hi>fooliſh,</hi> they be thought; remember this,</l>
               <l>That, trueſt <hi>wiſdome,</hi> ſeemeth <hi>fooliſhneſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>worldly prudent men,</hi> when, God, forth brings</l>
               <l>To fool their <hi>wiſdome,</hi> deſpicable things.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men, hear <hi>fools</hi> gladly, when themſelves are wiſe,</l>
               <l>And, meekly pity rather then deſpiſe</l>
               <l>Their folly, learning, thereby, ſometimes too,</l>
               <l>More, then by their own <hi>wiſdome,</hi> they could do:</l>
               <l>But, <hi>wiſe, mad fooliſh,</hi> or, what ev'r I am,</l>
               <l>To do this <hi>work,</hi> into the world I came;</l>
               <l>To theſe <hi>times,</hi> was reſerv'd; to this <hi>end,</hi> taught;</l>
               <l>And, to the ſight of many things, am brought,</l>
               <l>Which, els I had not known, nor would have ſeen,</l>
               <l>But, that, I ty'd, (as by the leg) have been,</l>
               <l>(<hi>Ten years</hi> together, <hi>ten dayes</hi> work to do)</l>
               <l>To <hi>know</hi> them, whether I ſo would or no.</l>
               <l>And, when I knew them, I would fain have done</l>
               <l>My own <hi>work</hi> firſt, or els, like <hi>Jonas</hi> run</l>
               <l>To <hi>Tarſis,</hi> or <hi>Lundee,</hi> or any whither</l>
               <l>(Adventuring through <hi>Seas,</hi> and <hi>Tempests</hi> thither)</l>
               <l>Much rather, then to have proceeded on,</l>
               <l>In doing that, which I, at laſt, have done.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:116012:4"/>
               <l>For, I am like the <hi>world,</hi> in many things,</l>
               <l>And, oft ſo tempted by her promiſings</l>
               <l>Of <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>ſafety,</hi> in another <hi>courſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That, I, with much ſtrife, did my heart inforce,</l>
               <l>To proſecute her <hi>duty;</hi> as ye may,</l>
               <l>Perceive, if, <hi>you</hi> the following <hi>tract</hi> ſurvay.</l>
               <l>But, my own <hi>thoughts,</hi> would neither let me ſleep,</l>
               <l>Nor ſuffer me a <hi>waking-peace</hi> to keep,</l>
               <l>Or, follow my <hi>affairs</hi> (though they were brought</l>
               <l>Neer to a point, of coming quite to nought)</l>
               <l>Till, I, my <hi>muſings,</hi> had in <hi>words</hi> array'd</l>
               <l>To be, by <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>other men,</hi> ſurvay'd.</l>
               <l>All thoſe <hi>affairs,</hi> aſide, I, therefore threw,</l>
               <l>To cloth my <hi>meditations,</hi> for your view;</l>
               <l>Which, being finiſh'd, I can now lye down</l>
               <l>And ſleep, as well as any man in Town.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>times</hi> are dangerous; and, I am told,</l>
               <l>By that which is my <hi>Guide,</hi> I ſhould not bold</l>
               <l>Beyond <hi>diſcretion</hi> be; which makes me talk</l>
               <l>In <hi>riddles,</hi> and with this <hi>Dark Lantern</hi> walk:</l>
               <l>That, I may ſee my way, and not be ſeen</l>
               <l>By ev'ry one, whom I may meet, between</l>
               <l>My goings <hi>out,</hi> and <hi>in:</hi> and that it may</l>
               <l>Give <hi>light</hi> to ſome, who are beſide their way,</l>
               <l>As I occaſion find; and, where I ſee</l>
               <l>The <hi>light</hi> that's offer'd, may accepted be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, what my <hi>viſions</hi> are, as in relation,</l>
               <l>Unto this <hi>Parliaments</hi> perpetuation</l>
               <l>I plainly ſhall unfold; becauſe, it may</l>
               <l>Concern you all, with good adviſe to weigh.</l>
               <l>Yea, fearleſly, my free thoughts, I will ſhew,</l>
               <l>What <hi>liking,</hi> or diſlike, ſoe're enſue.</l>
               <l>For, though to all <hi>intents</hi> by me deſign'd,</l>
               <l>They may not reach; it much contents my mind,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:116012:5"/>
               <l>That I have freed my <hi>ſoul.</hi> by thus imploying</l>
               <l>My <hi>Talent,</hi> to an inward reſts injoying;</l>
               <l>And, rais'd a <hi>Witneſſe</hi> up, that may declare</l>
               <l>To <hi>future times;</hi> what GOD'S proceedings are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If this find <hi>acceptation,</hi> it will be</l>
               <l>A <hi>ſign</hi> of future peace, to <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If, you reject it; I will fit my <hi>mind</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To bear the <hi>troubles,</hi> which are yet behind:</l>
               <l>Bewail, our manifold procraſtinations,</l>
               <l>Of GOD'S intended <hi>bleſſings,</hi> to theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Poſſeſſe the <hi>little portion,</hi> I have got</l>
               <l>As <hi>lost,</hi> or, els, as if I had it not;</l>
               <l>And, ſtrive to wean my <hi>heart,</hi> from things abroad,</l>
               <l>To ſeek my <hi>reſt;</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> alone in GOD:</l>
               <l>A <hi>refuge,</hi> ſo ſecur'd to me, that, neither</l>
               <l>My <hi>frailties, faults,</hi> or <hi>foes;</hi> or theſe together:</l>
               <l>Or <hi>friends,</hi> or <hi>Truſtees</hi> failings, either may</l>
               <l>Hazard, or forfeit; tear, or fool away.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt faithfull Remembrancer, <hi>Geo. Wither.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116012:5"/>
            <head>A DARK-LANTERNE, OFFERING A Dim Diſcovery, in <hi>Riddles, Parables,</hi> and <hi>Semi-riddles,</hi> intermixt with <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Remembrances,</hi> and <hi>Predictions,</hi> as they were promiſcuouſly, and immethodically re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to their <hi>Author,</hi> in his <hi>ſolitary muſings,</hi> the third of <hi>November</hi> 1652. about <hi>midnight.</hi> And, concluding with the <hi>Reſult</hi> of a <hi>Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Viſion,</hi> revealing a probable means of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, even this preſent Parliament, to be both <hi>perpetuall,</hi> and <hi>acceptable</hi> to theſe <hi>Nations</hi> to the end of the <hi>World.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <l>He, <hi>that goes</hi> with <hi>this LIGHT, his way may find:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Him, <hi>that</hi> againſt it <hi>comes, it maketh blind.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>HE, from whoſe perfect Light, all true <hi>Lights</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>Spake <hi>Parables;</hi> yea, ſpake nought els, to ſome;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Providence,</hi> by many various wayes,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>diſpenſation,</hi> to the <hi>world</hi> convayes</l>
                  <l>The means, of carrying on, thoſe <hi>works</hi> which tend</l>
                  <l>To <hi>man's perfection,</hi> at his <hi>later end;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, to the wónderfull accompliſhment,</l>
                  <l>Of what, <hi>eternally</hi> is his <hi>intent;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116012:6"/>
                  <l>Bringing oft times about, the <hi>ſelf-ſame things,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or, ſuch like) towards their accompliſhings;</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>prudent men,</hi> might underſtand thereby</l>
                  <l>What <hi>he</hi> deſigns, and therewith all comply.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Jacobs</hi> Off ſprings (who, for many ages</l>
                  <l>Were <hi>figures, types, examples,</hi> and preſages</l>
                  <l>For <hi>future times,</hi> and <hi>ſtates</hi>) became perverted,</l>
                  <l>And, grew to be ſo blind, and ſtubborn hearted,</l>
                  <l>As to deſpiſe the <hi>warnings, precepts, cautions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And good <hi>adviſe,</hi> which for their preſervations</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Prophets</hi> had perſpicuouſly declar'd;</l>
                  <l>GOD, juſtly, ſent unto them afterward,</l>
                  <l>His mind in <hi>Parables,</hi> whereof but few</l>
                  <l>The <hi>meanings,</hi> or <hi>interpretations</hi> knew:</l>
                  <l>And as they more and more, from him declin'd,</l>
                  <l>(And, from the <hi>truth</hi>) the more he couch'd his mind</l>
                  <l>In <hi>dark expreſſions,</hi> till they nothing ſaw</l>
                  <l>But what their <hi>pleaſure</hi> made to be a <hi>Law.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prince, Prophet, Priest,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> then, became</l>
                  <l>Wholly corrupt; a ſcandall, and a ſhame</l>
                  <l>To their <hi>Profeſſions,</hi> and to all their <hi>Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By an unlimited prevarication;</l>
                  <l>Whereby, the means ordained to recure them,</l>
                  <l>Was rendred inſtrumentall to obdure them,</l>
                  <l>By their own <hi>fault,</hi> and thoſe <hi>hypocriſies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, juſtly, drew a <hi>vail,</hi> before their eyes.</l>
                  <l>For, whereas, uſually in times preceding,</l>
                  <l>GODS <hi>errands,</hi> were made plain, at their firſt he eding,</l>
                  <l>So, alſo, were their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> then,</l>
                  <l>Renowned, wiſe, and honorable men,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n in their <hi>outward being;</hi> which, did add</l>
                  <l>Repute to that, which in command, they had:</l>
                  <l>But, <hi>He ardſmen,</hi> and <hi>fruit-gatherers,</hi> afterward</l>
                  <l>(With ſuch as brought no motives of regard,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116012:6"/>
                  <l>According to the <hi>fleſh</hi>) were ſometime ſent;</l>
                  <l>Which, in their <hi>hearers,</hi> did but ſcorn augment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, thus, <hi>contempt</hi> increas'd: the <hi>truths</hi> then told,</l>
                  <l>Were not alone, wrapt up in manifold</l>
                  <l>Strange <hi>ambiguities, obſcure expreſſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dark <hi>Metaphors,</hi> or much beclouded <hi>Viſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which few could underſtand; but, ſome, likewiſe</l>
                  <l>Illuſtrated their <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>Prophecies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or, rather vailed them) with <hi>circumſtances,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, did inlarge their hearers ignorances;</l>
                  <l>As alſo their <hi>diſdains:</hi> for, otherwhile,</l>
                  <l>They perſonated things, abſurd, and vile,</l>
                  <l>In vulgar apprehenſion: ſuch as ſeem</l>
                  <l>Deſerving rather <hi>ſlighting,</hi> then <hi>esteem;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea ſuch, ſometimes, as <hi>wicked</hi> did appear</l>
                  <l>To thoſe, who <hi>morally</hi> men righteous were:</l>
                  <l>As when, they were made <hi>ſignes</hi> unto that <hi>Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of their <hi>ſhame, nakedneſſe,</hi> or <hi>deſolation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of GODS <hi>laſting love,</hi> although they had,</l>
                  <l>By their <hi>adulteries,</hi> him <hi>jealous</hi> made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> he, formerly hath done,</l>
                  <l>GOD will proceed with us; and hath begun</l>
                  <l>Already, ſo to judge (and viſit here)</l>
                  <l>As he did <hi>them,</hi> when they rebellious were.</l>
                  <l>He, ſo, by <hi>changes,</hi> moves us to repent;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>judgements</hi> blends with <hi>mercies,</hi> to th' intent</l>
                  <l>That, he, into capacity might wooe us</l>
                  <l>Of that great <hi>good,</hi> which he deſires to do us.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This,</hi> makes him, ſometime <hi>ſmile,</hi> and ſometime <hi>frown;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now, <hi>raiſe us up;</hi> to morrow, <hi>pull us down:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This day,</hi> he, to our <hi>ſtrongeſt enemies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Renders us dreadfull: They, whom we deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That night</hi> triumph; and make us glad to fly</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Into</hi> our <hi>chambers,</hi> and there ſneaking lie;</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116012:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116012:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116012:8"/>
                  <l>Whil'ſt they deride, inſult, affront and jeer us,</l>
                  <l>Who, ſome few hours before, did greatly fear us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, makes him often fool our wiſdome ſo,</l>
                  <l>That, we are at a <hi>non plus,</hi> what to do;</l>
                  <l>And, then, in our diſtreſſe, to make our <hi>want,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weakneſſe,</hi> and <hi>failings,</hi> more predominant</l>
                  <l>For our <hi>deliverance,</hi> in a fatall hour,</l>
                  <l>Then all our <hi>wealth,</hi> our <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and our <hi>power.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This,</hi> makes him lead us through the <hi>wilderneſſes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>doubts, diſpairings, troubles,</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To our deſired <hi>Canaan,</hi> as be led</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Choſen</hi> heretofore; and, as he did</l>
                  <l>To them in their reſpective aberrations,</l>
                  <l>So hath he done, and will do, with theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As their, right ſo, our <hi>Princes,</hi> for oppreſſions</l>
                  <l>Are driven from their <hi>Thrones,</hi> and their poſſeſſions,</l>
                  <l>To eat (ev'n with confuſion of their faces)</l>
                  <l>Their bread with ſcarcity, in uncouth places;</l>
                  <l>Where, peradventure, they were mindfull made</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe <hi>forewarnings,</hi> which they timely had.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our <hi>Lords</hi> (as their <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> foretold,</l>
                  <l>When they had greateſt likelyhood to hold,</l>
                  <l>And to encreaſe their <hi>greatneſſe</hi>) this day, ſee,</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Houſe of Parliament,</hi> deſtroy'd to be,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n by <hi>it ſelf;</hi> and, that they are become</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vagrants abroad,</hi> or, els <hi>deſpis'd at home.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of their <hi>Pallaces</hi> and <hi>Piles of State,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are ras't, defac't, or left quite deſolate,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Zim,</hi> and <hi>Jim;</hi> for <hi>Vermine</hi> and ſuch fowls,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Dawes,</hi> and <hi>Ravens;</hi> great and little <hi>Owls.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our <hi>Prieſts,</hi> that were the gloriouſt <hi>Hirarchy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And proud'ſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> next the Papacy;</l>
                  <l>(Who, by the ſame pen warned, did return</l>
                  <l>Sharp perſecutions, injuries and ſcorn)</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116012:8"/>
                  <l>Are now deſpoil'd of all the pomp they had,</l>
                  <l>Diſhonor'd, poor, and deſpicable made.</l>
                  <l>Their fair <hi>Cathedrall Temples</hi> ſtand forſaken,</l>
                  <l>With ſtill increaſing <hi>ruines,</hi> rent and ſhaken;</l>
                  <l>And, in their ſteeds, thoſe <hi>perſons</hi> are deputed,</l>
                  <l>Whom they moſt hated, and moſt perſecuted.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Threats</hi> long ſince pronounced, now prevail,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> are become the <hi>tail;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And meer Mechanicks made <hi>diſpenſers</hi> are</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe things, which to them committed were:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perſons,</hi> of ſo <hi>mean guifts,</hi> and ſmall reſpect,</l>
                  <l>That, truth out of their mouths, gets but neglect;</l>
                  <l>Except with ſuch, as undervalue not</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Good wine,</hi> though offered in an <hi>earthen pot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For our <hi>unthankfulneſſe,</hi> and diſregard</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>nobler Teachers,</hi> whom, we long have heard,</l>
                  <l>Without improvement; for, <hi>hypocriſies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Meer <hi>outſide worſhip,</hi> and <hi>formalities,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>prayers, fasts,</hi> and <hi>praiſes;</hi> and, for, giving</l>
                  <l>That which coſt <hi>nothing,</hi> for great <hi>boons</hi> receiving:</l>
                  <l>For our <hi>backſlidings,</hi> and, then, <hi>perſevering</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>frequent ſinning,</hi> after <hi>frequent bearing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>actions,</hi> not agrecing with our <hi>ſaying:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>painting, guilding,</hi> and for <hi>overlaying</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Corrall ſtructures,</hi> with <hi>fain'd piety:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>Falſe gold,</hi> producted by our <hi>Chymeſtry</hi>)</l>
                  <l>For falſifying, with a brazen brow,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſerious promiſes,</hi> which we did vow</l>
                  <l>To GOD and <hi>men,</hi> before the face of heaven,</l>
                  <l>When we into extremities were driven:</l>
                  <l>For adding to <hi>devouring ſlames,</hi> more <hi>fuell:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For being, in our very <hi>mercies,</hi> cruell:</l>
                  <l>For turning careleſſy, our <hi>eyes,</hi> and <hi>ears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Widdows</hi> prayers, and from <hi>Orphans</hi> tears:</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116012:9"/>
                  <l>Yea, though <hi>Remembrancers</hi> did (as it were)</l>
                  <l>In publike, often pull us by the ear,</l>
                  <l>To mind it; yea, where many <hi>ſtanders by,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obſerv'd it; and, our groſſe ſtupidity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For theſe things; and, for many ſuch as theſe</l>
                  <l>God, having ſpoken to us, in our dayes,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>ordinary Preachers;</hi> now, begins</l>
                  <l>By <hi>others,</hi> to reprove us for our ſins:</l>
                  <l>Not only ſuch, as <hi>reaſon</hi> may allow,</l>
                  <l>Though called from the <hi>Shop board,</hi> or the <hi>Plough;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, ſuch, as we ſeem juſtly to contemn,</l>
                  <l>As making <hi>truths</hi> adhor'd, which come from them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ſteed of <hi>Teachers,</hi> train'd up in the <hi>Schools</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Arts,</hi> and of the <hi>Prophets; children fools,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Women</hi> and <hi>madmen,</hi> we do often meet,</l>
                  <l>Preaching, and threatning <hi>Judgements,</hi> in the ſtreet:</l>
                  <l>To ſome, pronouncing <hi>bleſſings;</hi> to ſome, <hi>woe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Scatt'ring their <hi>bread,</hi> and <hi>money,</hi> as they goe,</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as need; (though, in appearance, none</l>
                  <l>Can poorer be, then they, when that is gone:)</l>
                  <l>Yea, by ſtrange <hi>actions, poſtures, tones,</hi> and <hi>cryes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Themſelves they offer to our <hi>cars</hi> and <hi>eyes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As <hi>ſigns</hi> unto this <hi>Nation,</hi> of ſome things</l>
                  <l>Thereby <hi>portended;</hi> which (although this brings</l>
                  <l>Contempt upon their <hi>perſons</hi>) may be ſo,</l>
                  <l>For ought, the wiſeſt of us, yet doth know;</l>
                  <l>As were thoſe <hi>actions,</hi> perſonated by</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Prophets,</hi> whom the <hi>Jewes</hi> did vilifie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It may be on that <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> which they find,</l>
                  <l>Within their <hi>bearts,</hi> a ſuddain <hi>light</hi> hath ſhin'd,</l>
                  <l>Reflexions making, of ſome things to come,</l>
                  <l>Which leave within them, <hi>muſings</hi> troubleſome</l>
                  <l>To their <hi>weak ſpirits;</hi> or, too intricate</l>
                  <l>For them to put in order, and relate;</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116012:9"/>
                  <l>As they will eaſily believe on whom,</l>
                  <l>Such, more then naturall, <hi>out-beamings,</hi> come)</l>
                  <l>And, that, hath peradventure, thruſt them on</l>
                  <l>To act, as men in <hi>extaſies</hi> have done;</l>
                  <l>Striving, their <hi>Cloudy Viſions</hi> to declare</l>
                  <l>(And, of what conſequence, they think they are)</l>
                  <l>Till they have loſt the <hi>Notions,</hi> which they had,</l>
                  <l>And, want but few degrees, of being <hi>mad.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, <hi>Providence</hi> permitteth, to correct</l>
                  <l>Our deafneſſe, and our former diſreſpect</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>nobler instruments,</hi> whoſe <hi>lights</hi> did ſhine</l>
                  <l>More clearly; and, who, laying <hi>line,</hi> to <hi>line;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Precept,</hi> to <hi>Precept; in</hi> and <hi>out of ſeaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Taught reaſonably, ev'n <hi>truth's,</hi> tranſcending <hi>reaſon:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, els, it hath permitted been, to make us</l>
                  <l>Leſſe heedfull, of the <hi>plague,</hi> that may or'etake us;</l>
                  <l>By <hi>tokens,</hi> and by <hi>ſymptoms,</hi> to us giving,</l>
                  <l>That, ſeem not worth our <hi>heeding,</hi> or <hi>believing.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, I, perhaps, among <hi>theſe,</hi> may be <hi>one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That was let looſe, for ſervice to be done,</l>
                  <l>In order to ſuch <hi>kinds:</hi> (as, I believe</l>
                  <l>I am; as when I am gone, ſome will perceive,</l>
                  <l>Though, none obſerve it now) For, though I dreſſe</l>
                  <l>The <hi>mind,</hi> and <hi>matter,</hi> of my <hi>meſſages,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>meaſur'd words,</hi> with ſome ſuch other <hi>fancies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As are allowed in <hi>Poetick frenzies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, paſſe for ſober <hi>garbs:</hi> yet, now and then,</l>
                  <l>I blunder out, what <hi>worldly prudent men</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Count <hi>madneſſe;</hi> and, what, oft, the beſt men, too,</l>
                  <l>Diſlike awhile, and wiſh me not to do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, I beſt know my <hi>warrant;</hi> and proceed</l>
                  <l>As I am mov'd, with little fear, or heed,</l>
                  <l>What others judge: for, till ſome <hi>ſlips,</hi> or <hi>errors</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Expoſe me, to be liable to <hi>terrors,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116012:10"/>
                  <l>Ther's nothing, to my <hi>hurt,</hi> can dreadfull be,</l>
                  <l>Save my own <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>be</hi> that gave it me.</l>
                  <l>And, as this makes me, <hi>madly</hi> ſeem to dare;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n ſo, that ſeeming <hi>madneſſe,</hi> doth prepare,</l>
                  <l>And draw ſome, out of <hi>novelty,</hi> to heed,</l>
                  <l>What, they had never, els, vouchſaf'd to read:</l>
                  <l>And, theſe my <hi>ridlings</hi> now, are an <hi>invention</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſigned partly, unto that intention;</l>
                  <l>And, partly likewiſe, to amaze thoſe <hi>Readers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, to my <hi>purpoſes,</hi> are <hi>counter-pleaders.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When, others think, the <hi>times</hi> afford me may</l>
                  <l>Enough to ſpeak of, I have nought to ſay:</l>
                  <l>When my <hi>heart</hi> calls upon me, I caſt by</l>
                  <l>My own <hi>affairs,</hi> and to that <hi>call</hi> apply,</l>
                  <l>As I occaſions find, uttring ſometimes,</l>
                  <l>My thoughts in <hi>proſe,</hi> another while in <hi>rimes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One while, by <hi>ſharp,</hi> and <hi>bitter ſtrains</hi> reproving;</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, by <hi>admonitions,</hi> calm, and loving;</l>
                  <l>Yea, <hi>Jigs</hi> of <hi>recreation,</hi> ſometimes ſidling;</l>
                  <l>And, now, I'm faln into a fit of <hi>Ridling.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riddle my Riddles,</hi> then, you, that have heard</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Truths,</hi> oft, and plainly ſpoke without regard,</l>
                  <l>(Except it were, in <hi>miſchioſs,</hi> to combine</l>
                  <l>Againſt their <hi>peace,</hi> who caſt their Pearles to <hi>ſwine</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riddle</hi> them if you can: For, in them lies,</l>
                  <l>A dim <hi>character</hi> of our <hi>destinies.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Within theſe <hi>Problemes,</hi> thoſe things couched are,</l>
                  <l>Which I, once thought, more plainly to declare:</l>
                  <l>But, from that <hi>purpoſe,</hi> have now chang'd my mind,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>ſeeing,</hi> you might <hi>ſee,</hi> yet ſtill be blind:</l>
                  <l>That, you might <hi>read,</hi> and yet not <hi>underſtand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>work,</hi> which GOD and <hi>men,</hi> have now in hand:</l>
                  <l>Or, which of thoſe things will be <hi>firſt,</hi> or <hi>laſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt, <hi>future fates</hi> appear by what is <hi>paſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116012:10"/>
                  <l>And, that, your <hi>miſinter pretations</hi> may</l>
                  <l>Produce thoſe <hi>good effects,</hi> which you delay:</l>
                  <l>For, to that purpoſe, all, which I unfold,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hiſterologically</hi> ſhall be told.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yon,</hi> likewiſe, who oft read, in ſerious wiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shiptons Predicts,</hi> and <hi>Merlins Prophecies;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, vain <hi>conjectures,</hi> from the <hi>conſtellations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherewith, <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> have long fool'd theſe <hi>Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Neglecting that, the while, which both <hi>foreſeen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, <hi>brought to paſſe,</hi> in your own dayes, hath been:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riddle thoſe Riddles;</hi> or, at leaſt peruſe them,</l>
                  <l>And, if you find them frivolous, refuſe them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riddle</hi> theſe <hi>Riddles</hi> too, ev'n <hi>you,</hi> that ſeek</l>
                  <l>The <hi>common-peace,</hi> with hearts upright and meek:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You,</hi> that have underſtanding to diſcern</l>
                  <l>The <hi>preſent times;</hi> and, willing are to learn</l>
                  <l>Good leſſons from a <hi>Piſmire:</hi> For, to <hi>you,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By this <hi>Dark Lantern,</hi> I ſhall give a view,</l>
                  <l>Of things <hi>far off,</hi> and <hi>rubs</hi> now in your way,</l>
                  <l>Whereat, through want of <hi>light,</hi> you ſtumble may:</l>
                  <l>And, likewiſe, of <hi>effects,</hi> whereto, perchance,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You,</hi> by theſe <hi>glimmerings,</hi> may raiſe <hi>advance.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Obſerve them well, without enquiring, what</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Authors</hi> meaning was, in <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till, you <hi>your ſelves,</hi> have ſearch'd, how they <hi>in reaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Suit our <hi>affairs,</hi> our <hi>perſons,</hi> and the <hi>ſeaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>According to your <hi>judgements:</hi> for, that, ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be ſomewhat to the <hi>purpoſe,</hi> though not <hi>all.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, where no ſenſe that's likely, you can rear,</l>
                  <l>Leave it, as that, which lies without your <hi>ſphear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, that, which SHALL BE, will receive a <hi>being,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From each diſſenting <hi>Readers</hi> diſagreeing;</l>
                  <l>From that mans <hi>knowledge,</hi> who the ſenſe hath got;</l>
                  <l>From that mans <hi>ignorance,</hi> who knowes it not;</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116012:11"/>
                  <l>And he that <hi>would,</hi> and he that <hi>would not</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Shall help effect, what GOD intends to do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus, through a <hi>long lane,</hi> I have drawn you in,</l>
                  <l>Where my new <hi>Grove of Riddles</hi> doth begin,</l>
                  <l>With, now and then, a <hi>plain Lawn</hi> intermixt,</l>
                  <l>And, here and there, a ſmall <hi>ſherewood</hi> betwixt;</l>
                  <l>With ſuch <hi>digreſſions,</hi> that, you'l ſometimes doubt,</l>
                  <l>Whether I lead you, further <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>out.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, 'tis a <hi>wild plot,</hi> where are <hi>walks,</hi> and <hi>bowers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made for my own <hi>content,</hi> as well as yours:</l>
                  <l>And, if they tedious ſeem, you may be gone</l>
                  <l>At next <hi>low gap,</hi> you ſee, and no harm done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>harveſt</hi> of our <hi>Aera</hi> now drawes near,</l>
                  <l>And, faithfull <hi>Labourers</hi> will then appear</l>
                  <l>To order that <hi>fair field,</hi> where in was ſown</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Corn,</hi> which now with <hi>tares</hi> is overgrown:</l>
                  <l>And, to diſtinguiſh <hi>Wheat,</hi> from that which had</l>
                  <l>Reſemblance of it, both in <hi>ſtalk,</hi> and <hi>blade.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, ev'ry day, <hi>Impostors</hi> creeping in,</l>
                  <l>Will, by <hi>pretended holineſſe,</hi> begin</l>
                  <l>To plant <hi>themſelves;</hi> ſeeking their <hi>luſts</hi> to feed,</l>
                  <l>By ſcattering <hi>adulterated-ſeed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And lab'ring, to deſtroy thoſe <hi>means,</hi> whereby</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Truth</hi> may appear in perfect purity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In little time, ſhall many <hi>changes</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>interchanges,</hi> which will make men ſee</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>wiſdome</hi> to be <hi>folly;</hi> their chief <hi>might,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Flat <hi>feebleneſſe;</hi> their high eſteemed <hi>light</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Meer <hi>darkneſſe;</hi> and, that, moſt things by them done,</l>
                  <l>Will have <hi>effects,</hi> which they nev'r thought upon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In that <hi>Catholicon,</hi> or <hi>Mithridate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Providence,</hi> confected hath of late.</l>
                  <l>To temper, or diſpell, what hath diſeas'd</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Body Politike;</hi> it hath been pleas'd</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116012:11"/>
                  <l>(As finding it, a <hi>mixture</hi> requiſite)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vipers,</hi> and <hi>mortall poyſons,</hi> to unite</l>
                  <l>With <hi>wholeſome things;</hi> yea, <hi>mineralls</hi> and <hi>mettle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Steel,</hi> fixt matter, to unſettle:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Serpents brains,</hi> with faithfull <hi>Turtles hearts:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Lions, Lambs,</hi> and <hi>Foxes,</hi> ſome choice parts:</l>
                  <l>Somewhat of <hi>Hares,</hi> that ſwift and fearful be:</l>
                  <l>Somewhat of <hi>Snailes,</hi> in whom we nothing ſee,</l>
                  <l>But ſlowneſſe, and, by well compounding theſe,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>cure</hi> preparing is, for our diſeaſe:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fire, Water, Earth,</hi> and <hi>Ayr,</hi> (though diſagreeing,</l>
                  <l>In qualities) if well mixt, give a <hi>being</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>that,</hi> which cannot <hi>be,</hi> by any <hi>one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, any <hi>two,</hi> or <hi>three</hi> of theſe alone:</l>
                  <l>And, ſo, at laſt, ſhall ev'ry <hi>contradiction,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Among us, add ſome <hi>Dos,</hi> to our perfection:</l>
                  <l>Yea, they who <hi>pulldown,</hi> and they who <hi>erect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall in the <hi>cloſe,</hi> concur in one <hi>effect;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, <hi>he,</hi> who's <hi>all in all,</hi> may have due praiſe</l>
                  <l>By ev'ry <hi>contradiction</hi> in our wayes;</l>
                  <l>And, that, out of their <hi>diſcords,</hi> he may bring</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Diapaſon,</hi> making ev'ry thing</l>
                  <l>Aſſent together, in the conſummation</l>
                  <l>Of his <hi>deſignment,</hi> at the worlds <hi>creation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, whil'ſt this <hi>medicine</hi> fermenting lies,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>wheels</hi> of <hi>temp'r all contrarieties</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Move on; and, ev'ry day, abroad will ſend</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Productions,</hi> few, diſcerning to what <hi>end:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, yet, each <hi>individuall circumſtance,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Somewhat, the <hi>Grand-deſignment,</hi> ſhall advance,</l>
                  <l>Yea, <hi>foolings, failings, fraud,</hi> and <hi>treachery</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As well as <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>true ſincerity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall add thereto; and, herein, will alone,</l>
                  <l>The diff'rence be; ſuch, as have juſtly done</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116012:12"/>
                  <l>Their <hi>duties;</hi> and, in doing them perſever,</l>
                  <l>(Or, willingly, and knowingly endeavour</l>
                  <l>As they are able) will enjoy the <hi>bliſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, they who counter-operate ſhall miſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I.G.N.R.N.S. with, other ſome,</l>
                  <l>Such like, confederated are become,</l>
                  <l>To ruine this <hi>Republike;</hi> and, have laid</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deſignes,</hi> whereby it may be ſoon betray'd,</l>
                  <l>And, infamous, inſenſibly, become,</l>
                  <l>With all <hi>wiſe men</hi> abroad, and here at home.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe</hi> (though but few obſerve it) have, long, had</l>
                  <l>A purpoſe theſe three <hi>Ilands</hi> to <hi>invade;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, to poſſeſſe them, with a <hi>people</hi> far</l>
                  <l>More barbarous then <hi>Kernes,</hi> and <hi>Redſhanks</hi> are.</l>
                  <l>Some of their <hi>Party,</hi> to promote their <hi>ends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do yet appear to be our faithfull <hi>friends;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, into every place of <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>confederates</hi> have thruſt.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Townes</hi> and <hi>Boroughs, Cittadells</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Courts,</hi> and <hi>Councells,</hi> and in all <hi>Committees;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In offices of <hi>profit,</hi> and <hi>command,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Throughout the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> at <hi>Sea,</hi> and <hi>Land</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They have <hi>Abettors;</hi> and, ſo bold they grow</l>
                  <l>That, every man almoſt, their aimes may know;</l>
                  <l>And, their <hi>attempts,</hi> although but <hi>fools</hi> they are</l>
                  <l>Are at this preſent time, improv'd ſo far</l>
                  <l>That, they have ſhaken that, wherein conſiſts,</l>
                  <l>Our honor, and our nobleſt <hi>intereſts;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And into practiſe, they begin to draw</l>
                  <l>Among us here, the <hi>Clagefurtian</hi> Law.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>M.N.O.P. <hi>Demas, Diotrophes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peripateticks, Stoicks, Phariſees,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With others, who, in judgement diff'ring be,</l>
                  <l>Will, altogether, as one man agree,</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116012:12"/>
                  <l>To fortifie their <hi>private intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Indangering (by what ſhall be poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Unduly) that, which is to others due:</l>
                  <l>Untill the <hi>faithfull Shepherds</hi> do purſue</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>claim</hi> aright; the ſame deriving from</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Foſter-Fathers,</hi> whence, it firſt did come;</l>
                  <l>And, of whom, it was long ſince propheci'd</l>
                  <l>That, GOD, by them, a <hi>portion</hi> would provide</l>
                  <l>For thoſe, he ſends forth, to preſerve the <hi>beauty</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>holineſſe,</hi> when, man, forgets his duty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some other <hi>accidents,</hi> time will beget</l>
                  <l>Which may be mark'd out, by our <hi>Alphabet:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By,</hi> and <hi>for</hi> envy, jealouſie, and pride,</l>
                  <l>Shall, A. B. C. be laid awhile, afide.</l>
                  <l>Deſpiſed alſo, V. and I. ſhall be</l>
                  <l>P P. and S. againſt C S. and P.</l>
                  <l>Shall then conſpire; and, for a <hi>Salve</hi> employ</l>
                  <l>That, which it ſelf, and all things, doth deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> help not more</l>
                  <l>Then all the other letters, did before:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>common helps,</hi> will be apply'd in vain,</l>
                  <l>The fury of their <hi>madneſſe,</hi> to reſtrain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The cauſes, whence this hazard will ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Are ſuch as this; obſerve it, and be wiſe.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Gods,</hi> which heretofore</l>
                  <l>Stood open to the prayers of the poor,</l>
                  <l>Is cloſed up, and few admitted in,</l>
                  <l>But, ſuch as are conveyed by a <hi>gin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Contriv'd ſo narrow, that the people ſay</l>
                  <l>It was choak'd up, the firſt, or ſecond day:</l>
                  <l>And, with diſtemper, they exclaim, that this</l>
                  <l>Of all their <hi>grievances,</hi> the greateſt is:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it puts their patience, to more trialls,</l>
                  <l>Then, if of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> they had quick <hi>denialls:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116012:13"/>
                  <l>Turnes <hi>hopes</hi> into <hi>deſpairs;</hi> converts their <hi>lives</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>living deaths,</hi> their <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lmes</hi> to <hi>coroſives.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Saints</hi> likewiſe, that muſt propitiate,</l>
                  <l>On their behalfs, and offer at the gate</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>juſtice</hi> and of <hi>mercy,</hi> their petitions</l>
                  <l>Are not ſo ſenſible of their <hi>conditions;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor from all <hi>partiality</hi> ſo free</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Mediators</hi> alwayes ought to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, makes one grumble in his privacies;</l>
                  <l>Another, gapes out open <hi>blaſphemies:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some, with ſuch indignation filled are,</l>
                  <l>As, if they <hi>Giant-like,</hi> would make a warre</l>
                  <l>Againſt their GODS (if, lookers on, may gueſſe,</l>
                  <l>By their diſtempers, of their purpoſes)</l>
                  <l>And, univerſally, there is a <hi>cry</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So lamentable, and rais'd up ſo high,</l>
                  <l>That, if theſe <hi>Deities,</hi> ſhall not in time,</l>
                  <l>With due compaſſion, bow their ears to them,</l>
                  <l>And, their juſt <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>requeſts</hi> fulfill,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A higher power,</hi> theſe plaints examine will,</l>
                  <l>And theſe <hi>inferiour Gods,</hi> ſhall tumble then,</l>
                  <l>From heav'n like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and die like men:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riddle this Riddle,</hi> and reſolve me whether</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Temple,</hi> be <hi>Pantheon,</hi> or ſome other,</l>
                  <l>Wherein <hi>Subdeities,</hi> invoked are:</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Temple</hi> e're it be; we wiſh it were</l>
                  <l>More open; leſt upon thoſe <hi>Gods,</hi> it bring</l>
                  <l>Contempt, or worſe, and ruines ev'ry thing</l>
                  <l>To them ſubordinate: for, hence doth flow</l>
                  <l>Moſt other <hi>grievances,</hi> complain'd of now;</l>
                  <l>And, hence riſe thoſe <hi>confuſions,</hi> which increaſe</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>troubles,</hi> and procraſtinate our peace.</l>
                  <l>From hence is it, mens <hi>ſuits</hi> prolonged are</l>
                  <l>Beyond their lives; and after <hi>twice five year,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116012:13"/>
                  <l>As far from ending, as when they begun;</l>
                  <l>Yea, endleſſe, till poor <hi>Suiters</hi> are undone,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At theſe words, an <hi>Illuſion</hi> cry'd, <hi>take heed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, further do not in this ſtrain proceed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt, ſome <hi>Interpreters,</hi> interpret, ſo,</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Riddles,</hi> that the <hi>Ridler</hi> they undo.</l>
                  <l>The ſuddain <hi>caution,</hi> ſtartled me a while;</l>
                  <l>Yet, back return'd it with a ſtrong recoil;</l>
                  <l>Suggeſting, that I over-much bewray'd</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>nakedneſſe;</hi> and them too open laid</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſhame I ought to hide, and, that ſo far</l>
                  <l>It may provoke them, who ſoon angry are,</l>
                  <l>As thereby to indanger at the leaſt,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>quiet,</hi> and my <hi>private interest.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How, therefore, this <hi>objection</hi> I paſt over,</l>
                  <l>E're further I proceed, I'le here diſcover.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Againſt theſe <hi>doubts,</hi> my <hi>Genius</hi> up aroſe,</l>
                  <l>And, quite out of my heart, their poyſon throws;</l>
                  <l>Aſſuring me, I had no cauſe to fear</l>
                  <l>What other mens <hi>interpretations</hi> were;</l>
                  <l>Or, to ſuppoſe the ſafety of this <hi>Nation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were not more worthy of a preſervation</l>
                  <l>Then their <hi>repute,</hi> who are quite ſenſleſſe growne,</l>
                  <l>Both of the <hi>publike danger,</hi> and their owne.</l>
                  <l>Or think it better that a generall</l>
                  <l>Diſeaſe o'reſpread us, rather, then to call</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Scab,</hi> a <hi>Scab,</hi> or, timely to declare</l>
                  <l>The cure of theſe things, which deſtructive are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It <hi>told me,</hi> (and with arguments not weak)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>cauſe,</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> requir'd me now to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Without reſpect of perſons; and, that, I</l>
                  <l>Was bound unto it by my <hi>fealty.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It <hi>told me,</hi> 'twas a <hi>duty</hi> whereunto</l>
                  <l>I was ordain'd; and, which I'm kept to do.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116012:14"/>
                  <l>It <hi>repreſents unto me,</hi> from what ſtrong</l>
                  <l>And ſpitefull <hi>Adverſaries;</hi> and, how long,</l>
                  <l>I have preſerved been, ſince I begun</l>
                  <l>To do ſuch <hi>works,</hi> when they were to be done.</l>
                  <l>It <hi>bids me</hi> to record, by what ſtrange wayes,</l>
                  <l>(And means unlikely) I have all my dayes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deliverances</hi> obtain'd; ev'n when I had,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> that might make a <hi>wiſe man</hi> mad;</l>
                  <l>And, not one <hi>friend,</hi> me, in thoſe ſtreights to own,</l>
                  <l>But, ſuch as GOD ſtill rais'd me up unknown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It bids me mind, how oft (when I have had</l>
                  <l>No other help) his <hi>Providence</hi> hath made</l>
                  <l>The <hi>malice of my fees,</hi> things to project</l>
                  <l>Againſt me, which my <hi>ſuccour,</hi> did effect;</l>
                  <l>And, without which, I probably had loſt</l>
                  <l>Juſt <hi>expectations,</hi> with much pain and coſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It bids me mark, how many there are ſtill,</l>
                  <l>(Who, without cauſe, have born me evill will)</l>
                  <l>That daily do expect to ſee me ſtumble,</l>
                  <l>When they may add a kick, to make me tumble:</l>
                  <l>How, in thoſe <hi>High Aſſemblies,</hi> where they deem,</l>
                  <l>It may moſt diſadvantage my eſteem,</l>
                  <l>They whiſper out <hi>detractions;</hi> or, ſpeak loud</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things, which cannot juſtly be avow'd:</l>
                  <l>How <hi>enviouſly,</hi> they often make relations</l>
                  <l>Of what GOD gives, beyond their expectations;</l>
                  <l>With ſuch periphraſes, as may infer</l>
                  <l>That, my <hi>ſupplies,</hi> were got as ill as their.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It wills me, likewiſe, ſeriouſly to heed,</l>
                  <l>How, they in other things, with me proceed;</l>
                  <l>How, by their <hi>ſpight,</hi> all publike favours done me.</l>
                  <l>Bring nought, as yet, but coſt, and troubles on me,</l>
                  <l>Which had e're this deſtroy'd me, had I not</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Preventions,</hi> from a <hi>Power</hi> above them got;</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116012:14"/>
                  <l>And, by theſe <hi>mercies,</hi> it conjures me to</l>
                  <l>What, <hi>conſcience,</hi> and my <hi>judgement,</hi> bids me do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It minds me to be mindfull of that <hi>powre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which hath preſerv'd in every <hi>evill hour.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How plentifully, I have ſtill been fed.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n when I ſaw not means, of next dayes <hi>bread</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, what was in their hands, who would not ſpare,</l>
                  <l>The leaſt <hi>ſupply,</hi> when moſt diſtreſt we were.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How, my <hi>repute,</hi> with <hi>good men,</hi> was maintain'd,</l>
                  <l>When with <hi>unjuſt aſperſions,</hi> I was ſtain'd:</l>
                  <l>And, when our <hi>Princes,</hi> on their <hi>Judgement Seats,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thundred againſt me, nothing leſſe then <hi>threats.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It <hi>charmes,</hi> to obſerve, that, though I get</l>
                  <l>Little or nothing, of that <hi>publike debt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which was aſſign'd, and which hath now been due</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ten years</hi> (by claimes approved juſt and true,</l>
                  <l>On <hi>treble trialls</hi>) and, though ever ſince,</l>
                  <l>It yeelds me nought, but troubles and expence;</l>
                  <l>That GOD, hath naytheleſſe, improv'd of late,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Mite,</hi> into a competent eſtate;</l>
                  <l>Meerly, by ſuch unlikely means, as thoſe</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Jacob</hi> us'd, when in the <hi>watering troughs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He laid his <hi>whit led ſticks,</hi> till he was paid</l>
                  <l>The <hi>wages,</hi> which his Maſter had delaid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It calleth on me, to look back upon</l>
                  <l>Thoſe works, which have within my dayes been done;</l>
                  <l>(And chiefly thoſe, which ſtand in ſome relation</l>
                  <l>Unto <hi>my ſelf,</hi> together with this <hi>Nation</hi>)</l>
                  <l>What <hi>ſtrange effects,</hi> and <hi>unbelieved things,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have followed my <hi>fore conjecturings:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What <hi>riſings,</hi> and what <hi>fallings,</hi> I have heeded:</l>
                  <l>What <hi>mercies,</hi> and what judgements have ſucceeded</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>various paths.</hi> It urgeth me to weigh,</l>
                  <l>What may bety'd me, if I diſobey</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116012:15"/>
                  <l>The <hi>motions of my heart,</hi> and what <hi>event</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He may expect, who ſhall be negligent</l>
                  <l>To do his <hi>duty,</hi> when his <hi>eye</hi> perceives</l>
                  <l>What GOD intends; and, when his heart believes,</l>
                  <l>He dreams not; but, is really required</l>
                  <l>To act, according, as he is inſpired:</l>
                  <l>And, ſomewhat tells me, that, if after all</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>mercies,</hi> and <hi>remembrances,</hi> I fall</l>
                  <l>From my <hi>reſolves;</hi> GOD juſtly may expoſe,</l>
                  <l>And leave me, to the malice of my foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Leſt, yet, my <hi>frailties,</hi> or <hi>ſelf interest,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>carnall reaſons,</hi> ſomewhat might ſuggeſt</l>
                  <l>To blow all this away; it, comes ſometimes,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>midnight</hi> (as it did of late) and chimes</l>
                  <l>Dreadfull <hi>Alarms,</hi> which, do awaking keep</l>
                  <l>Mine eyes, when other men are faſt aſleep:</l>
                  <l>From <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> then, it freſh advantage taking,</l>
                  <l>(And from vain thoughts, which too oft keep me wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king)</l>
                  <l>Thus, it invades me; what is that, which thou</l>
                  <l>Li'ſt muzing on, and ruminating now?</l>
                  <l>Art thou contriving, how to lay <hi>foundations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For thine own <hi>family,</hi> when <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are tumbling down? and, when impartiall <hi>fates,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are overthrowing <hi>Monarchies,</hi> and <hi>States?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is this a time to ſettle, when there are</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> that ſhake the <hi>mountains,</hi> ev'ry where?</l>
                  <l>Is this a time to <hi>plant,</hi> when thunder-ſtrokes,</l>
                  <l>Root up <hi>high Cedars,</hi> and break down <hi>ſtrong Okes?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is this a time to <hi>purchaſe,</hi> when the trouble,</l>
                  <l>And hazards, make the payments more then double?</l>
                  <l>Or wheel thee (as by triall thou haſt found)</l>
                  <l>Into a fruitleſs and a tedious round?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, if a <hi>ſeaſonable time,</hi> it be</l>
                  <l>For others, can it ſo befall to <hi>thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116012:15"/>
                  <l>Whil'ſt thou delayeſt his <hi>affairs,</hi> from whom,</l>
                  <l>The means to make thy <hi>purchaſes,</hi> muſt come?</l>
                  <l>When, GOD, to build thy <hi>houſe,</hi> hath now begun,</l>
                  <l>Wil't then, to finiſh it to others run?</l>
                  <l>As if, <hi>he,</hi> who from <hi>nothing,</hi> heretofore</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus far,</hi> hath brought thee, now, could do no more?</l>
                  <l>Oh take good heed, what <hi>courſe,</hi> thou doſt purſue,</l>
                  <l>(And, what neglect) leſt els, thy <hi>courſe,</hi> thou rue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God, hath already, made thee to poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>The <hi>gates</hi> of thoſe that were thine <hi>enemies:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by a <hi>means unlooked for,</hi> reſtor'd</l>
                  <l>That, which was taken from thee by the <hi>Sword:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Houſes,</hi> by others built, to thee are granted,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Orchards</hi> and <hi>Gardens,</hi> which thou haſt not planted,</l>
                  <l>He gives, in recompenſe for what was loſt</l>
                  <l>In <hi>publike ſervice;</hi> yea, without the coſt</l>
                  <l>Of this <hi>Republike;</hi> and, had more beſtowne</l>
                  <l>E're now, perhaps, if thou to do thine <hi>owne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had'ſt not delay'd <hi>his work,</hi> and, to thy <hi>hope</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For this (it may be) he will put a <hi>stop.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why, then, with <hi>frnitleſſe muſings,</hi> buſied are</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>thoughts,</hi> on what, muſt be anothers care?</l>
                  <l>Deferring that, which thou art call'd unto,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeking daily, ſomewhat els to do?</l>
                  <l>Art thou afraid, leſt thou thereby may'ſt loſe</l>
                  <l>Thy late <hi>recruits?</hi> or, reinrage thy foes?</l>
                  <l>Or, marr thy <hi>quiet?</hi> curſed is that fear;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>thou</hi> too, if therein thou perſevere:</l>
                  <l>For, when a <hi>temp'r all bleſſing,</hi> makes us worſe,</l>
                  <l>It is a <hi>plague,</hi> beyond a <hi>tem'prall curſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, if thou take not heed will quite deprive thee</l>
                  <l>Of that which <hi>Providence,</hi> did freely give thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, who are they? or, where inhabit thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who dare to take away, what, GOD, beſtowes</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116012:16"/>
                  <l>If thou adhere to him? whom need'ſt thou fear,</l>
                  <l>If in thy duty, thou ſhalt perſevere?</l>
                  <l>Nay, rather, which of <hi>thoſe,</hi> that ſeem to be</l>
                  <l>Moſt <hi>dreadfull,</hi> ſhall not be afraid of thee</l>
                  <l>If he be guilty? and who (though on high</l>
                  <l>He bears his head) ſhall not, in privacy,</l>
                  <l>Think on thy <hi>lines,</hi> with <hi>trembling,</hi> when he hears</l>
                  <l>What they declare, and what his <hi>conſcience</hi> fears?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>thou,</hi> ſaid my <hi>good Angell,</hi> haſt not, yet,</l>
                  <l>Quite ſhaken off, thy <hi>fears,</hi> and <hi>fanting fit;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conſider, wiſely, of this <hi>Generation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In thoſe things, which have thereto, nigh <hi>relation:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sum up together, that, which thou haſt heeded</l>
                  <l>In thoſe thou <hi>fear'st:</hi> mark, how they have proceeded;</l>
                  <l>What, they <hi>have been;</hi> what, at this <hi>time,</hi> they <hi>are;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What, they <hi>may be,</hi> before they are aware;</l>
                  <l>What, they <hi>deſign,</hi> in what <hi>paths</hi> they are going;</l>
                  <l>What, they have <hi>done;</hi> what, they are daily <hi>doing;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What <hi>Labyrinths</hi> involve them; what, <hi>confuſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Encloſe them round, as alſo what <hi>concluſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are following; and, then, thou wilt not fear</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>power</hi> as <hi>foes,</hi> nor for their friendſhip care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, ſtill, ſome <hi>outward intereſt,</hi> be that</l>
                  <l>Which thou deſir'ſt to ſave; conſider, what</l>
                  <l>Thereto conduceth: for, ſometimes, the <hi>thing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We fear to looſe, is <hi>kept</hi> by <hi>hazarding:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, loſt in ſeeking to preſerve the ſame,</l>
                  <l>By other <hi>means,</hi> then that, through which it came.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, <hi>thou,</hi> permit the <hi>proud,</hi> without a check</l>
                  <l>To follow their <hi>career,</hi> they'l break, their neck.</l>
                  <l>And, with <hi>themſelves</hi> (as our <hi>affairs,</hi> now ſtand)</l>
                  <l>Indanger all the people of this Land.</l>
                  <l>Where, then, wilt thou be ſafe? or, where wilt thou</l>
                  <l>Injoy with peace, what thou poſſeſſeſt now?</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116012:16"/>
                  <l>But, if a <hi>word in ſeaſon,</hi> thou ſhalt ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>Who knows, what <hi>inſtruments deſpis'd and weak</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May compaſſe? and, who knows, but that, of <hi>them,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, heretofore thy <hi>cautions</hi> did contemn.</l>
                  <l>Some, touch'd may be, with ſenſe of their condition,</l>
                  <l>And, turn back, from the <hi>path-wayes</hi> of <hi>Perdition?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, who knows not, that many may be found</l>
                  <l>(Whoſe <hi>actions</hi> blameleſſe are, whoſe <hi>faiths</hi> are ſound)</l>
                  <l>That, by theſe <hi>hints,</hi> may hart and courage take.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> from their dreamings, to awake?</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, therein thy <hi>duty</hi> having done,</l>
                  <l>If any be ſecur'd, thou ſhalt be <hi>one.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When theſe things were inſpir'd, and duly weigh'd,</l>
                  <l>My heart, which was a little while diſmay'd</l>
                  <l>From proſecuting, what I had begun,</l>
                  <l>Aſſum'd new courage, and went boldly on:</l>
                  <l>And, theſe <hi>expostulations,</hi> may perchance,</l>
                  <l>Some others, to the like <hi>reſolves</hi> advance</l>
                  <l>On like <hi>occaſions;</hi> unto which intent,</l>
                  <l>Theſe few ſhort ſteps, beſide my way I went:</l>
                  <l>For I confeſſe, my <hi>theam</hi> I following not,</l>
                  <l>Have rambled out, as if I had forgot</l>
                  <l>What I at firſt propoſed; and inſteed</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Riddles,</hi> to plain language do proceed.</l>
                  <l>But, I will wheel about, and with the <hi>rein</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Turn <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> into his path again;</l>
                  <l>Though, he, in his <hi>digreſſions</hi> (as we ſay</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Beggers</hi>) never is beſide his way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Once on a time</hi> (thus did <hi>old tales</hi> begin,</l>
                  <l>E're I was born, or thought I ſhould have been)</l>
                  <l>A <hi>fooliſh people</hi> over much at eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>wantonneſſe,</hi> and <hi>vanity</hi> to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Among their <hi>may-games,</hi> brought home from the <hi>wood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Trees,</hi> which had els, till now, unheeded ſtood.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116012:17"/>
                  <l>Of <hi>theſe,</hi> they made, by <hi>hewings, knocks,</hi> and <hi>ſmoothing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, look like ſomething, which reſembled nothing.</l>
                  <l>And, out of knotty, <hi>ſhapeleſſe logs,</hi> did hew</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>ſtatues</hi> not uncomely to the view.</l>
                  <l>Theſe, e're quite ſhaped, with ſome <hi>jeers,</hi> and <hi>mocks,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They ſet up higher, upon other blocks.</l>
                  <l>Then, them repoliſhed, and painted ſo,</l>
                  <l>That, of what <hi>ſtuffe</hi> they were, few men could know.</l>
                  <l>Beginning then, their own work, to admire,</l>
                  <l>They rais'd them higher ev'ry day and higher,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Idols</hi> they became; with whom, they grew</l>
                  <l>At firſt, familiar, and did them beſtrew</l>
                  <l>With <hi>flowers</hi> and <hi>garlands:</hi> ſhortly after, they</l>
                  <l>Bow'd humbly down before them, ev'ry day;</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>custome,</hi> had their judgement more befool'd;</l>
                  <l>But, then (when <hi>theſe,</hi> miſhrin'd they did behold,</l>
                  <l>Sparkling with <hi>Jewells,</hi> and with gold aray'd)</l>
                  <l>They, of their own <hi>Creations,</hi> grew afraid.</l>
                  <l>And, at the laſt, (as at the laſt, all do</l>
                  <l>That whoring after their own <hi>fancies</hi> go;)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe fools,</hi> repented of their <hi>ſuperſtition;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bewail'd the ſlavery, of their condition;</l>
                  <l>With ſome appearances, of an intent</l>
                  <l>To grow more <hi>wiſe,</hi> as well as to repent:</l>
                  <l>Yea, to <hi>blaſpheme,</hi> their new made GODS they ſpar'd not,</l>
                  <l>And, would have pul'd them down again, but <hi>dar'd not.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, by their <hi>flattring attributes</hi> (long, given)</l>
                  <l>They had advanc'd them, to a <hi>ſphere,</hi> or <hi>heav'n,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where, uncontroul'd, a power they exercis'd</l>
                  <l>According to their <hi>luſt;</hi> and thoſe deſpis'd</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>hands</hi> had made them, &amp; whoſe <hi>breath</hi> had blown them</l>
                  <l>Too high, for their <hi>ambitiouſneſſe,</hi> to own them.</l>
                  <l>Yea, by their <hi>incantations,</hi> theſe, had brought</l>
                  <l>Strong <hi>ſpirits,</hi> into what their hands had wrought;</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116012:17"/>
                  <l>Inliv'ning, and enabling them unto</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>actions,</hi> which their <hi>makers</hi> might undo.</l>
                  <l>Yet, perſevere, this <hi>blockiſh</hi> people will</l>
                  <l>To make ſuch <hi>idols,</hi> and advance them ſtill;</l>
                  <l>Till both they, and their <hi>idols</hi> are deſtroy'd</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe the GOD of Gods, my fears makes void.</l>
                  <l>For, moſt men being of a <hi>ſlaviſh</hi> mind,</l>
                  <l>Are nat'rally to <hi>ſlaviſhneſſe</hi> inclin'd:</l>
                  <l>And to fulfill their bruitiſh luſt will fawn</l>
                  <l>Upon a Dog, and lay their ſouls to pawn.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riddle</hi> this <hi>Riddle,</hi> if you can, and tell</l>
                  <l>What <hi>People,</hi> this may be, and where they dwell:</l>
                  <l>Which I believing you with eaſe may do,</l>
                  <l>Will add this following <hi>Parable</hi> thereto.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There was a time, when ſilly <hi>Bees</hi> could ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>(A people, of much induſtry, though weak)</l>
                  <l>And, theſe, among themſelves, made grievous moans,</l>
                  <l>As being much oppreſſed, by their <hi>drones;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who (having made intruſions among thoſe</l>
                  <l>That had an uncontroulable diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Of their <hi>Republike</hi>) did in ſundry wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Incroachments make on their <hi>proprieties;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, greedily, unto themſelves derive,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>fatneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> of the <hi>hive.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Complaints in private,</hi> no redreſſe obtaining,</l>
                  <l>Increaſt to <hi>open,</hi> and <hi>avow'd complaining:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which finding like ſucceſſes, they begun</l>
                  <l>To <hi>buz,</hi> as when their <hi>ſwarming time,</hi> draws on:</l>
                  <l>Then, to <hi>ſhut up their cells,</hi> to <hi>ſhake their wings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>leave their wonted work,</hi> and <hi>ſhew their ſtings.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Drones,</hi> at firſt, were ſtartled much thereat;</l>
                  <l>But, being not ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> as they are <hi>fat;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Neglected ſtill, the <hi>courſe</hi> which might prevent</l>
                  <l>The <hi>miſchief</hi> then appearing imminent:</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116012:18"/>
                  <l>Which, when I ſaw, I would no longer ſtay;</l>
                  <l>But, ſaid, GOD <hi>help them;</hi> and ſo come away.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Parable,</hi> if rightly moralliz'd,</l>
                  <l>Affords a meaning not to be deſpis'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſo doth this which follows: as I went</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> unto the <hi>Parliament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſperſed in my way, I ſaw the <hi>cocks,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which kept the <hi>hens,</hi> and <hi>capons</hi> from the <hi>fox</hi>)</l>
                  <l>With broken wings, with backs, without a feather</l>
                  <l>To hide their naked bodies, from the weather;</l>
                  <l>With plumeleſſe <hi>tails,</hi> with ſcarred <hi>necks</hi> and <hi>brests;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With empty <hi>bellies,</hi> and with <hi>combs,</hi> and <hi>creſts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cut quite away; and ſcraping with their <hi>feet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On dunghills, for their food, and in the ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>So deſpicably, that it could appear</l>
                  <l>By nothing ſave their <hi>ſpurs,</hi> what once they were:</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Popinjaies,</hi> and <hi>Parrets,</hi> cloath'd and fed,</l>
                  <l>By what the <hi>valour</hi> of theſe purchaſed,</l>
                  <l>(And, trim'd with ill got <hi>feathers</hi>) ſtrutted by,</l>
                  <l>Caſting upon them a <hi>diſdainfull eye:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which when I ſaw, methought (I tell you true)</l>
                  <l>It was no good preſage; pray, <hi>what think you?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>News,</hi> if you look for, I but little know,</l>
                  <l>Save, ſuch as this next <hi>Parable</hi> doth ſhow.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>fair ſhip,</hi> now lies floting on the floods,</l>
                  <l>Well fill'd with <hi>Paſſengers,</hi> well fraught with goods,</l>
                  <l>Labring to fix an <hi>Anchor</hi> on the ſtrand</l>
                  <l>Of her wiſh'd <hi>harbor,</hi> which lies neer at hand.</l>
                  <l>By many ſtormes, much <hi>tackling,</hi> ſhe hath ſpent;</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Maſts</hi> are ſhater'd; and her <hi>ſhrowds</hi> are rent:</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>ammunition,</hi> and her <hi>ſtores</hi> are waſted,</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>bevorage</hi> is evill taſted:</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>keel</hi> ſprings leaks, through her uncawked <hi>ſeams;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her <hi>knees</hi> are weakned, bruized are her <hi>beams:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116012:18"/>
                  <l>Her <hi>Pump</hi> is broke, no <hi>Cable</hi> ſound hath ſhe;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Anchors</hi> have been ſlipt, till none there be:</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Helm</hi> hangs looſe, her <hi>Cards</hi> have great defects;</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>compaſſe</hi> likewiſe often miſdirects:</l>
                  <l>And ev'ry where, ſhe crazineſſe doth feel,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Prow</hi> to <hi>Stern,</hi> from <hi>topmaſt,</hi> to the <hi>Keel.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In this condition, too and fro ſhe drives,</l>
                  <l>And, on the waves, with much ado, yet <hi>lives:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, now of late again, the <hi>Seas</hi> go high;</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſtiff gale</hi> blows, and ſhe expos'd doth lye</l>
                  <l>To many hazards, cloſe without the <hi>Bar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Betwixt two <hi>Forelands,</hi> which in kening are:</l>
                  <l>If ſhe were <hi>fitted,</hi> forth again to ſtand</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Seaward, Pyrats</hi> threaten; if to <hi>Land</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She makes; the rocks lye ſcattered, here and there,</l>
                  <l>In which, as great, or, greater dangers are:</l>
                  <l>And, which is worſe, they, who in her abide,</l>
                  <l>Are <hi>mutinous;</hi> and, ſom what els beſide:</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>ignorant,</hi> ſome <hi>trecherous,</hi> and, ſome</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ambitious,</hi> how, poſſeſſors to become</l>
                  <l>Of what is other mens: yea, ſome of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who, have this goodly ſhip at their diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>Have in delayes, their <hi>time,</hi> and ſtores, miſpent,</l>
                  <l>For private ends; or, for accompliſhment</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>worſe deſignes:</hi> and, in this great diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>(In part through <hi>fear,</hi> in part through <hi>guiltineſſe</hi>)</l>
                  <l>So much amuz'd, and ſo amuzed are,</l>
                  <l>That, they are at a loſſe, what <hi>courſe</hi> to ſteer,</l>
                  <l>Themſelves to ſave; and compaſſe their <hi>deſign;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Without which, to no <hi>courſe,</hi> they will incline</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Owners, and the Paſſengers, have waved</l>
                  <l>No means, whereby this <hi>Veſſell</hi> might be ſaved:</l>
                  <l>For, to that purpoſe, they have not alone,</l>
                  <l>Put hand, to all things needfull to be done;</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116012:19"/>
                  <l>And, faithfully, unto their labour ſtood;</l>
                  <l>(Ev'n with the frequent hazard of their blood)</l>
                  <l>But alſo, willingly away have caſt</l>
                  <l>Their goods; yea, ſome have thrown forth to the laſt</l>
                  <l>Of all their outward <hi>viſible eſtates:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Few of her <hi>Maſters,</hi> or her <hi>Maſters Mates,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In her extremities, adventring ought;</l>
                  <l>Although their <hi>Cabbins,</hi> with rich goods are fraught.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The danger ſtill increaſeth; and thoſe few</l>
                  <l>In place of <hi>truſt,</hi> who to their <hi>truſt</hi> are true,</l>
                  <l>Perceiving all endeavours rendred vain</l>
                  <l>By their decreaſe, to whom doth appertain</l>
                  <l>That <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſells</hi> charge; they labour'd ſeriouſly</l>
                  <l>To find out an expediment, whereby</l>
                  <l>Some other <hi>Pilots</hi> might be timely ſent</l>
                  <l>Their neer approaching ſhipwrack, to prevent.</l>
                  <l>And, that by making of their <hi>Canons</hi> roar,</l>
                  <l>They might invite help, from the <hi>neighbring ſhore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>motion</hi> pleaſed all, ſave ſuch as had</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Self-ends</hi> to fear; and, theſe a <hi>faction</hi> made</l>
                  <l>So ſtrong againſt it; that, this <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſell,</hi> yet</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hulls</hi> there, with many perills, round beſet;</l>
                  <l>Not knowing (without hazard) either how</l>
                  <l>To ride ſafe, tack about, or venture through</l>
                  <l>The narrow Channell; whoſe hid winding lies</l>
                  <l>Obſcured from their knowledge, and their eyes:</l>
                  <l>And, one <hi>dark night,</hi> or, but one <hi>tempest</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>Might wrack her on the ſands, or on the ſhore.</l>
                  <l>But, maugre all theſe hazards; <hi>ſhe</hi> at laſt,</l>
                  <l>In her wiſh'd <hi>barbour,</hi> ſhall an anch or caſt;</l>
                  <l>For, to the <hi>Leeward,</hi> lies an <hi>unſeen Bay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where, through the ſoft <hi>Ouze,</hi> run aground ſhe may</l>
                  <l>Without a bruize; and, ſhall <hi>recruits</hi> take in,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n where 'twas fear'd, ſhe ſhould have ſplitted bin.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116012:19"/>
                  <l>You therefore, who conceive your intereſt</l>
                  <l>To be concern'd by what is here expreſt,</l>
                  <l>Priſe God alone, when fafe this <hi>Ship</hi> ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>For none could have ſecured her, but <hi>he.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let not thoſe, to whom the ſame relates</l>
                  <l>Slight what this <hi>Parable</hi> inſinuates,</l>
                  <l>Which next enſueth: for, it hath an uſe,</l>
                  <l>That much to their advantage may conduce.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>homebred Lion</hi> (of a hair unknown</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Africa</hi>) by being overgrown,</l>
                  <l>And dreadfull to his <hi>Keepers,</hi> will thereby</l>
                  <l>Awake the rage of <hi>ſmother'd jealouſie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And loſe his <hi>tail;</hi> except between his <hi>pawes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He couch his <hi>head,</hi> and hide his <hi>teeth</hi> and <hi>clawes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Rampant</hi> grow; and what will follow then?</l>
                  <l>Ask thoſe you credit, they are <hi>Cunning men:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>me</hi> you ask in vain; for 'tis my <hi>fate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seldome to be believ'd, till 'tis too late.</l>
                  <l>But that ſtout <hi>Lion</hi> by his prudency</l>
                  <l>May eaſily improve this <hi>jealouſie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both for the <hi>Publike ſafety,</hi> and th' increaſe</l>
                  <l>Of his own <hi>honor,</hi> alſo, if he pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>And I do probably preſume he will,</l>
                  <l>If my <hi>well-wiſhes,</hi> have not fool'd my <hi>skill.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before that time, they who have took delight</l>
                  <l>In <hi>deeds of darkneſſe,</hi> will put out the <hi>light</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By which the <hi>footſteps</hi> of their <hi>foes</hi> are known,</l>
                  <l>And whereby they might <hi>ſee</hi> to guide their <hi>own:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſteed whereof, perhaps erect they ſhall</l>
                  <l>An <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> which will hazard all.</l>
                  <l>To each man then ſhall <hi>Providence</hi> diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>That, which for his <hi>chief happineſſe</hi> he choſe:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>dogs,</hi> who to their vomit do retire,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>ſwine</hi> (who love to wallow in the mire)</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116012:20"/>
                  <l>Themſelves with their <hi>beloved fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h</hi> ſhall fill;</l>
                  <l>And they that are <hi>unclean,</hi> ſhall be ſo ſtill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>wilfull Adder,</hi> who doth ſtop his ears,</l>
                  <l>And will not heed the <hi>Charmer</hi> whom he hears,</l>
                  <l>Shall feel a <hi>voice</hi> within him, that will ſhake him</l>
                  <l>Out of his dumps; and from his deafneſſe wake him,</l>
                  <l>When 'tis too late to hear what might prevent</l>
                  <l>The dint of his forewarned detriment.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Leaches</hi> ſhall by <hi>ſalt</hi> a vomit take;</l>
                  <l>Or els continue ſucking, till they break.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Bubbles,</hi> who in <hi>emptineſſe</hi> do find</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>pleaſure,</hi> ſhall be puffed up with <hi>wind</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till (being blown to <hi>nothing</hi>) there appear</l>
                  <l>No <hi>ſignes,</hi> that in the world ſuch <hi>bladders</hi> were.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſons of earth,</hi> who with the <hi>Gods</hi> make war,</l>
                  <l>Shall heap up hills on hills, till cruſht they are</l>
                  <l>Ev'n by their own <hi>Deſignes;</hi> the <hi>Dogs</hi> that prey</l>
                  <l>Upon their <hi>Flocks,</hi> and tear their wool away,</l>
                  <l>Shall <hi>bark</hi> no more, but only <hi>ſnarle</hi> and <hi>grin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And run about the fields without a skin.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſhrubs</hi> and <hi>Briars,</hi> which more proud are grown,</l>
                  <l>Then were the <hi>Cedars,</hi> lately broken down;</l>
                  <l>Among their <hi>leaves</hi> and <hi>thornes,</hi> a <hi>fire</hi> do hide,</l>
                  <l>Which on a ſuddain will conſume their pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>grubs</hi> and <hi>maggots,</hi> but e're while ſo ſmall,</l>
                  <l>So poor and weak, that they could hardly crawl,</l>
                  <l>Have got <hi>bulk, ſtrength, new formes, aſpiring wings;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea dreadfull <hi>teeth,</hi> and <hi>horns,</hi> and <hi>claws,</hi> and <hi>ſtings:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, by a <hi>ſtorm,</hi> whereof they have no dread,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall conſume as faſt as they were bred:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within the circuit of our <hi>Northern Clime</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not long before, or after theſe, in time,</l>
                  <l>Out of the putrified <hi>barbed ſteed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall generated be a num'rous breed</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116012:20"/>
                  <l>Of noyſome <hi>hornets,</hi> which abroad will fly,</l>
                  <l>Much miſchief doing, and next winter die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Friends</hi> poſſibly may meet (our <hi>Proverb</hi> ſayes)</l>
                  <l>But <hi>mountains</hi> never; yet in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Proverb</hi>'s croſt: for <hi>hills</hi> have often met,</l>
                  <l>With purpoſe on each other to beget</l>
                  <l>A long'd for iſſue; and it is believ'd</l>
                  <l>By many, that they ſomewhat have <hi>conceiv'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of great <hi>concernment:</hi> but you'l ſee the <hi>birth</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prove nothing, but a <hi>moldring lump of earth;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(As they themſelves will be, till <hi>clay</hi> and <hi>duſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seek better things, then to fulfill their luſt:)</l>
                  <l>For none can anſwer now our expectation,</l>
                  <l>But that <hi>great hill,</hi> whence cometh our <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All this from objects which are found within</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Britiſh Orb,</hi> hath preconjectur'd bin;</l>
                  <l>But thoſe that follow next, to me appear</l>
                  <l>By things which I obſerve without our <hi>ſphere.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The blaſted <hi>Orange,</hi> and the <hi>crooked Vine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With many <hi>trees</hi> on either ſide of <hi>Rhine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall twiſt together, that beneath their <hi>ſhade,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A ſhelter for the <hi>Thiſtle</hi> may be made,</l>
                  <l>Till they perceive what <hi>curſe</hi> is in purſuit</l>
                  <l>Of that rejected <hi>plant,</hi> root, branch, and fruit;</l>
                  <l>And then they'l wiſer grow; leſt they may become</l>
                  <l>Expoſed juſtly to the ſelf-ſame doom.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mean while, the <hi>tawny Olive</hi> ſhall aſſay</l>
                  <l>His roots into thoſe <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>allies</hi> to convay,</l>
                  <l>From whence it was diſplanted; and effect</l>
                  <l>His purpoſe, by a <hi>Wile</hi> which few ſuſpect;</l>
                  <l>Except the <hi>Willow,</hi> and the <hi>Oke</hi> foreſee</l>
                  <l>What for their mutuall good ſhould thought on be:</l>
                  <l>And both the <hi>frogs</hi> and <hi>mice,</hi> which are in fight,</l>
                  <l>Be wary what is watch'd for by the <hi>Kite.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116012:21"/>
                  <l>By which means they ſhall break a <hi>grand deſign</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which is on foot, their States to undermine;</l>
                  <l>And they who of this <hi>Peace</hi> firſt movers are,</l>
                  <l>Shall of that bleſſing reap the greateſt ſhare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Obſerve this well: if ever you ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>(As poſſibly it may permitted be)</l>
                  <l>That from it <hi>height,</hi> the RED-CROSSE ſhall decline,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>half moon</hi> for that time ſhall <hi>Northward</hi> ſhine,</l>
                  <l>(With an ill influence upon the Seas)</l>
                  <l>Beyond the <hi>Pillars</hi> of great <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Southward</hi> not be retrograde again,</l>
                  <l>Till that a <hi>reaſcenſion</hi> ſhall attain.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>loſſes</hi> are ſometimes a gainfull <hi>prize;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>over-ſights,</hi> men grow to be more wiſe;</l>
                  <l>And they who know not yet what may concern</l>
                  <l>Their welfare, will perhaps more wiſdome learn,</l>
                  <l>When more experience makes their judgment ſtronger,</l>
                  <l>By ſuffering <hi>loſſe</hi> and <hi>ſcorn</hi> a little longer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We, on this ſide the <hi>water,</hi> are not yet</l>
                  <l>Confus'd enough that <hi>Order</hi> to beget,</l>
                  <l>Which muſt eſtadliſh us; and ſhall therefore</l>
                  <l>Purſue <hi>ſelf-intereſt,</hi> a little more.</l>
                  <l>With <hi>new wine</hi> our <hi>old bottle</hi> muſt be fil'd,</l>
                  <l>(Endangring <hi>wine</hi> and <hi>bottle</hi> to be ſpil'd)</l>
                  <l>Till ſuch as are in <hi>powre</hi> be pleas'd to hear</l>
                  <l>The counſell of a <hi>ſlighted engineer:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>new cloth</hi> our <hi>old garment</hi> patch'd muſt be,</l>
                  <l>(Whereby the <hi>rents</hi> made wider ye ſhall ſee)</l>
                  <l>Till every <hi>old rag</hi> be worn out, and then</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Robe</hi> ſo rent, ſhall be renew'd agen:</l>
                  <l>And they that own it, be ſecured more,</l>
                  <l>And much more dignifi'd, then heretofore;</l>
                  <l>If they who muſt compleat it make their <hi>choice.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>lot divine,</hi> as well as <hi>humane voice:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:116012:21"/>
                  <l>Whereto <hi>ſelf-ſeekers</hi> never will agree,</l>
                  <l>Untill inforced by ſome <hi>streights</hi> it be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when this comes to paſſe, there ſhall appear</l>
                  <l>A <hi>new light</hi> ſhining in our <hi>hemiſphere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That will diſperſe the <hi>clouds</hi> and <hi>fogs,</hi> which make</l>
                  <l>So many croſſe each other, and miſtake</l>
                  <l>The way of <hi>ſafety;</hi> then we ſhall perceive</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Oppoſites</hi> deſire to interweave</l>
                  <l>Their intereſts with ours; and to have ſhare</l>
                  <l>In that which God will for theſe <hi>Iſles</hi> prepare:</l>
                  <l>Wherein if we accord, we ſhall poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>Each other, and the world in Chriſtian peace;</l>
                  <l>Till he approacheth to aſcend the <hi>Throne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who muſt unite <hi>all Nations</hi> into <hi>one.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ſhall the <hi>blazing Comets,</hi> which have ſeem'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fixt ſtars,</hi> and been by many ſo eſteem'd,</l>
                  <l>(Ev'n of the greateſt magnitude) down from</l>
                  <l>Their heights be thrown; and more deſpis'd become</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Glowormes,</hi> or thoſe <hi>rotten chips,</hi> that glare</l>
                  <l>In <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> as if <hi>reall lights</hi> they were:</l>
                  <l>Then ev'ry <hi>ſingle perſon</hi> ſhall be brought</l>
                  <l>Unto his <hi>Test;</hi> and that which he hath wrought</l>
                  <l>Shall paſſe a <hi>fiery Triall,</hi> ſuch as were</l>
                  <l>Made fat with <hi>publike ſpoils;</hi> and <hi>cloathed</hi> are</l>
                  <l>By ruining of others; will that day</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>hungry, poor,</hi> and <hi>naked</hi> ſent away,</l>
                  <l>And rendred the ſcorn of ev'ry one,</l>
                  <l>Whom they oppreſt, deſpis'd, and trampled on.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then they, who large <hi>indulgences</hi> contrive</l>
                  <l>For others, that themſelves they may forgive;</l>
                  <l>Who cunning are, at <hi>fast</hi> and <hi>looſe</hi> to play;</l>
                  <l>Who <hi>take</hi> to <hi>morrow,</hi> what they <hi>give</hi> to <hi>day;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who make their <hi>ſeeming favours,</hi> means unto</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>miſchiefs,</hi> which their <hi>malice</hi> could not do.</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116012:22"/>
                  <l>Who <hi>Spider-like,</hi> weave <hi>cobwebs,</hi> with pretence</l>
                  <l>To catch the noyſome <hi>flies</hi> which give offence.</l>
                  <l>When none but harmleſſe <hi>Bees</hi> their <hi>engines take,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, through them <hi>waſps</hi> and <hi>hornets</hi> paſſage make.</l>
                  <l>They, who do ſacrifice unto the dead</l>
                  <l>That wherewithall the living ſhould be fed;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n when they (wanting what ſhould life preſerve)</l>
                  <l>Lie naked, harbourleſſe, and like to ſtarve.</l>
                  <l>And then ſuch as <hi>innocents</hi> cauſe betray,</l>
                  <l>And juſtifie the wicked, then ſhall they</l>
                  <l>Who add more <hi>greaſe</hi> to <hi>fatneſſe;</hi> and where's none</l>
                  <l>Scrap't off, the fleſh that's left unto the bone.</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall all theſe, and ſuch like, to their doom</l>
                  <l>With fear, with trembling, and amazement come,</l>
                  <l>And undergo deſerved puniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe beforehand timely they repent:</l>
                  <l>In which condition they may yet receive</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Remiſſion,</hi> and in future ſafety live.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then alſo they, who now are forc'd to take</l>
                  <l>The juiceleſſe apples of <hi>Aſphaltis Lake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Inſted of that which was the price of blood,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Limbs liberty,</hi> and of their livelyhood)</l>
                  <l>Shall better be rewarded; and confeſſe</l>
                  <l>There is a GOD that loveth <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then they who have received <hi>stones</hi> for <hi>bread,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>Scorpions</hi> for <hi>fiſh</hi>) ſhall with <hi>good things</hi> be fed.</l>
                  <l>Then they, who ſerv'd like <hi>Tantalus</hi> have bin</l>
                  <l>(With <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>waters,</hi> which their lips and chin</l>
                  <l>Have often touch'd in vain) ſhall that enjoy,</l>
                  <l>For which they fruitleſſe labours now employ:</l>
                  <l>Yea, they who got but <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>vineger,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When in their greateſt <hi>Agonies</hi> they were,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſee what <hi>Sampſons</hi> Riddle hath imply'd,</l>
                  <l>On them, and their oppreſſors verifi'd:</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116012:22"/>
                  <l>Out of their <hi>eaters</hi> carkaſſes, will meat</l>
                  <l>Extracted be; and ſweetneſſe they ſhall get</l>
                  <l>Out of the bones and ruines of the <hi>ſtrong,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By whom they formerly received wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ravenous <hi>Wolves,</hi> ſhall <hi>Lambs</hi> and <hi>Kidlings</hi> feed,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>thiſtly field</hi> ſhall bring forth pretious ſeed:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Crocodile</hi> ſhall tears of <hi>kindneſſe</hi> weep;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ramping Lion</hi> to the croſs ſhall creep:</l>
                  <l>And ſuch things as were noyſome heretofore,</l>
                  <l>Shall make our future benefit the more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then, from the <hi>buried Oxe,</hi> will forth ariſe,</l>
                  <l>A ſwarm of thrifty <hi>honey making flies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſhall with <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> and with <hi>plenty</hi> ſtore</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Ilands,</hi> from the <hi>midland,</hi> to the <hi>ſhore;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſpread their <hi>floting hives</hi> o're all the <hi>Seas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Twixt both the <hi>Tropicks,</hi> to th' <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And all without) that <hi>bleſſings</hi> which now are</l>
                  <l>Somewhere enjoy'd, may then be ev'ry where;</l>
                  <l>To make <hi>preparatives</hi> for that which brings</l>
                  <l>Into <hi>one body,</hi> all diſperſed things.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Other events, that ſeem of conſequence,</l>
                  <l>I do foreſee approachings, not far hence:</l>
                  <l>But ſo obſcurely, that I cannot ſay</l>
                  <l>(Without ſome doubtings) whereto tend they may</l>
                  <l>For, far beyond my apprehenſion lies</l>
                  <l>The chain of thoſe conceal'd contingencies</l>
                  <l>Which draw on <hi>future things:</hi> and that frail <hi>glaſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through which the <hi>light,</hi> diſcloſing them, muſt paſſe,</l>
                  <l>Is ſo defective, that it may perchance</l>
                  <l>Miſrepreſent them in ſome circumſtance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet by th' <hi>inlightnings,</hi> which the <hi>ſacred Writ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On <hi>ſanctified reaſon</hi> doth beget,</l>
                  <l>If we will weigh, conſider, and compare</l>
                  <l>Thoſe WORDS and <hi>works,</hi> which <hi>paſt</hi> and <hi>preſent are,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116012:23"/>
                  <l>To GOD and men relating; we of ſome</l>
                  <l>Things <hi>future,</hi> may aright inform'd become.</l>
                  <l>Yea, out of queſtion, by <hi>theſe</hi> are foreſhown</l>
                  <l>To all intents, as much as need be known,</l>
                  <l>Relating either to our private fates,</l>
                  <l>Or unto <hi>Kingdomes, Commonwealths,</hi> and <hi>States:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thereto, for the right end, men apply</l>
                  <l>Their ſenſe in <hi>faith,</hi> and with <hi>humility.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To find what ſenſe my <hi>Parables</hi> contain,</l>
                  <l>No man that's wiſe, ſhall need his wits to ſtrain;</l>
                  <l>For e're three years, are three moneths paſt the middle</l>
                  <l>Moſt men the meaning of them will unriddle,</l>
                  <l>Without an <hi>Oedipus;</hi> and think that he</l>
                  <l>Who made them, had <hi>Caſſandra</hi>'s deſtiny.</l>
                  <l>But theſe meer trifles are, reſpecting that</l>
                  <l>Of whoſe approach I tydings can relate:</l>
                  <l>For long it ſhall not be, e're that be done</l>
                  <l>Which will cut off all tyrannies in <hi>one:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea that which many thouſands have expected,</l>
                  <l>Hundreds of years, ſhall fully be effected,</l>
                  <l>Before the <hi>Wheel of Time,</hi> now rowling by</l>
                  <l>Hath paſt M. D. C. L. X. V. and I.</l>
                  <l>Which numbers how to calculate aright,</l>
                  <l>From this that follows take a little light.</l>
                  <l>Firſt, to begin it, you muſt learn to find</l>
                  <l>What <hi>year</hi> the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> firſt declin'd,</l>
                  <l>All whoſe Characters, us'd in <hi>numeration,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus plac'd, according to their <hi>valuation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Explain a <hi>mystery:</hi> for of that <hi>State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereto they did belong, they ſhew'd the date:</l>
                  <l>And at that ſeaſon 'twill compleated be,</l>
                  <l>In which <hi>Rome</hi> looks for her next JUBILEE.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My <hi>Ridling</hi> fit now leaves me for a time;</l>
                  <l>And here I'le put a period to my <hi>Rhime.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116012:23"/>
                  <l>My inward perturbations are paſt over,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>brains</hi> begin, by ſetling, to recover</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wits, whereby I may, like other men,</l>
                  <l>Converſe; and follow my affairs agen.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>night adventures</hi> I have paſſed thorow,</l>
                  <l>And they who meet me in the ſtreets to <hi>morrow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will ſearce believe how mad I was this <hi>night,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Untill they ſhall peruſe what I now write;</l>
                  <l>And moſt of them, will then, (it may be) deem,</l>
                  <l>That others are more mad, then I yet ſeem.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:116012:24"/>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:116012:24"/>
               <head>The Perpetuall PARLIAMENT. BEING The Reſult of a <hi>Contemplative Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> revealing a probable meanes of making this Parliament to be both perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and acceptable to theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if they ſo pleaſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Paradox, <hi>though this appear to ſome, Conſider it, leſt els, a</hi> miſchief <hi>come.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>IS that deſign'd? then it is time to vary</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Thems,</hi> leſt, on a ſuddain, all miſcarry.</l>
                  <l>Riddles adien, let clouds away be blown,</l>
                  <l>And my <hi>Dark Lantern,</hi> quite aſide be thrown;</l>
                  <l>That e're it be too late, I down may charm</l>
                  <l>The Spirits conjur'd up, to do us harm:</l>
                  <l>For in my <hi>contemplations</hi> I have had</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Viſion,</hi> which hath ſome diſcov'rie; made,</l>
                  <l>And in a <hi>plain ſong</hi> I intend to ſing,</l>
                  <l>How we may <hi>concord,</hi> out of <hi>diſcords</hi> bring,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Order</hi> out of <hi>confuſions,</hi> and reſtore</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Peace,</hi> whoſe late infringements we deplore;</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116012:25"/>
                  <l>Where, to begin the <hi>work;</hi> how to proceed,</l>
                  <l>That which is yet but words, may be a deed,</l>
                  <l>And to declare our means of <hi>ſettlement,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>to be an <hi>everlaſting Parliament.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It may appear, (and will be thought perchance)</l>
                  <l>At leaſt much raſhneſſe, if not arrogance,</l>
                  <l>That I adventure to employ my pen</l>
                  <l>Upon a <hi>ſubject,</hi> which more able men</l>
                  <l>Have hitherto declin'd, and which of late,</l>
                  <l>Hath ground adminiſtred of much debate,</l>
                  <l>(And much diſpute) to Counſells of renown,</l>
                  <l>Without a full <hi>reſolve,</hi> as yet made known:</l>
                  <l>But theſe are <hi>blaſts,</hi> whereof ſmall heed I take</l>
                  <l>For <hi>chaffe</hi> and <hi>feathers</hi> only, they can ſhake;</l>
                  <l>And he that all things hath at his diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>Is pleaſed ſome <hi>expedients</hi> to diſcloſe</l>
                  <l>To poor and ſimple perſons, now and then,</l>
                  <l>Which he conceals from <hi>wiſe,</hi> and <hi>noble men:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He, ſometimes calls men from within the grates,</l>
                  <l>To Counſell grave, and <hi>mighty Potentates;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And they in <hi>meekneſſe</hi> have embrac'd the ſame</l>
                  <l>Without a jealouſie of any ſhame</l>
                  <l>Which might thereby reflect diſparagements</l>
                  <l>Upon their wiſdome, from thoſe <hi>inſtruments.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor is there any cauſe, why ſuch as are</l>
                  <l>Made inſtrumentall, thoſe things to declare</l>
                  <l>Which may be ſerviceable, ſhould therefore</l>
                  <l>Eſteem their wiſdome, or themſelves the more;</l>
                  <l>Since they have nothing, but what they receive,</l>
                  <l>And are but <hi>earthen pipes,</hi> to help derive</l>
                  <l>To others, what into themſelves they take,</l>
                  <l>Not ſo much for their own, as others ſake.</l>
                  <l>And if aſſume ought to my ſelf I would,</l>
                  <l>I nothing know, that arrogate I could</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116012:25"/>
                  <l>By what ſhall be propoſed, more then they,</l>
                  <l>Who have not to this end a word to ſay,</l>
                  <l>If they deſire to ſerve you; when they ſhall</l>
                  <l>Meet ſuch occaſions, as I met withall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, as when two great <hi>Armies,</hi> long ingag'd,</l>
                  <l>Having each others fury ſo inrag'd,</l>
                  <l>That over all the fields there are beſpread,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diſorders</hi> rais'd out of <hi>deſpair</hi> and <hi>dread;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such renovations on the hills and vallies,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>charges</hi> and <hi>retreats;</hi> of <hi>routs and rallies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So loud a noyſe of <hi>drums,</hi> and <hi>guns,</hi> and <hi>eries;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such clouds of <hi>ſmoke</hi> and <hi>duſt</hi> to blind their eyes;</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>ſtops</hi> by them that <hi>ſlain</hi> and <hi>wounded</hi> ly,</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>througs</hi> and <hi>tumults</hi> among thoſe that fly,</l>
                  <l>And, ſuch <hi>confuſions,</hi> that the <hi>Chief Commanders</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Know not what courſe to take; if then, <hi>by-ſtanders,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Upon a <hi>neighb'ring hill,</hi> ſhall thence diſcern</l>
                  <l>Where ſome advantage lies, which may concern</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>friends ingag'd;</hi> and from among them <hi>one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall (ventring down) inform them what is done;</l>
                  <l>Where their foes weakneſs lies; and how they may</l>
                  <l>Rally their <hi>broken troops,</hi> and win the day,</l>
                  <l>What great thing hath he done, whereof to boaſt?</l>
                  <l>Or what diſhonor hath that <hi>Army</hi> loſt,</l>
                  <l>By his officiouſneſſe? or what's his gains</l>
                  <l>But knocks perhaps, or woundings for his pains;</l>
                  <l>From thoſe, it may be, of his <hi>Party</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Who know not what he thither came to do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is my caſe; who for ſuch <hi>ſervices,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And ſuch adventures heretofore as theſe)</l>
                  <l>Have gain'd ſo little, that none needs envy</l>
                  <l>The profit which I have receiv'd thereby;</l>
                  <l>Or, thoſe advantages I might expect,</l>
                  <l>If that which I propoſe ſhould take affect;</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116012:26"/>
                  <l>Conſidering, how many ſtill there be,</l>
                  <l>To make my beſt deeds miſchievous to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, whatſoever ſhall thereon ſucceed</l>
                  <l>With what is now intended, I'le proceed,</l>
                  <l>As my <hi>peculiar work;</hi> and to be done</l>
                  <l>By no man, if I let the ſame alone.</l>
                  <l>For, (as it by my <hi>Journall Books</hi> appears)</l>
                  <l>Somwhat above the term of forty years</l>
                  <l>I have been on the <hi>hills of contemplation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>voluntary Watchman</hi> for this <hi>Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I, oft, when none to ſecond me I knew.</l>
                  <l>In times of greateſt danger ſtood <hi>perdue.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I oft was pris'ner took, and did inlarge</l>
                  <l>My ſelf, at all times, at my proper charge.</l>
                  <l>I, more then once, to ſcape my Foes made ſhift,</l>
                  <l>With nothing, but my <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>raiment</hi> left;</l>
                  <l>And have perſwaded been (ev'n ever ſince</l>
                  <l>J reacht the years of ripe intelligence)</l>
                  <l>That (next unto his ſervice) GOD, in chief,</l>
                  <l>Gave me my being, faculties and life,</l>
                  <l>To ſerve my <hi>Country,</hi> and to have an eye</l>
                  <l>On thoſe who hindred her proſperity;</l>
                  <l>And, to imploy my ſtudies and my wit,</l>
                  <l>Jn ſearching out what might advantage it,</l>
                  <l>Though no man ſhould regard it; yea, though ſtill</l>
                  <l>J <hi>injuries</hi> receiv'd for my <hi>good will:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And this hath oft produc'd ſuch fruits as theſe,</l>
                  <l>Judge me, or uſe me for it as they pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>J ſhall, at laſt, be paid for all J do:</l>
                  <l>And, ſo ſhall they, who dare oppoſe it too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Having thus <hi>prefac'd,</hi> to anticipate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Miſcenſures,</hi> J, my <hi>Viſions</hi> thus relate.</l>
                  <l>When with ſad thoughts J many nights and dayes,</l>
                  <l>Had over-look'd my <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>others wayes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116012:26"/>
                  <l>Conſidering ſeriouſly, both what they were</l>
                  <l>And in what poſture, our <hi>affairs</hi> now are;</l>
                  <l>I ſaw ſo much <hi>confuſion,</hi> and <hi>diſorder,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Chaos daily, ſo much widing further</l>
                  <l>By <hi>new confuſions,</hi> and ſo few, that ſee</l>
                  <l>Or credit, in what hazards we now be,</l>
                  <l>That in theſe overwhelmings I almoſt</l>
                  <l>Was ſwallowed up, in danger to be loſt:</l>
                  <l>And doubtleſſe in thoſe <hi>whirlpools</hi> loſt had bin,</l>
                  <l>But that the <hi>clew,</hi> by which I ventur'd in,</l>
                  <l>Did bring me forth, and ſet me on a <hi>Station</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where I might view them, without <hi>perturbation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>ſafety</hi> too, and with ſo true a <hi>light</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, thereby plainly, I diſcover might</l>
                  <l>From whence this Chaos ſprings; and by what courſe</l>
                  <l>We might (if poſſible) drink up the ſource,</l>
                  <l>Or make ſome ſuch diverſion, as would win</l>
                  <l>An <hi>entrance,</hi> where <hi>good order</hi> might begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As I ſtood muſing, how this could be done,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>voice</hi> within me ſaid; this <hi>works</hi> for none</l>
                  <l>But him to do, who firſt did out of <hi>nought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bring <hi>ſomething;</hi> and from <hi>ſomething, all things</hi> brought.</l>
                  <l>Then ſaid my heart, LORD, though this <hi>work,</hi> to thee</l>
                  <l>Belongs alone, yet inſtruments there be,</l>
                  <l>By which thou workeſt all things here below;</l>
                  <l>Some inſtrumentall means, now therefore ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Whereby this may be done; and, then alone</l>
                  <l>Shal't reap that honor which infues thereon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Inſteed of <hi>vocall anſwer</hi> hereunto,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A firm perſwaſion,</hi> that it ſhould be ſo</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt my <hi>ſoul;</hi> and that he whoſoever</l>
                  <l>Would faithfully and ſeriouſly endeavour</l>
                  <l>A <hi>reſtauration,</hi> either ſhould acquire</l>
                  <l>The full accompliſhment of his deſire;</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116012:27"/>
                  <l>Or ſo much toward it, as might at leaſt</l>
                  <l>Secure him in his noble intereſt.</l>
                  <l>Herewith well ſatisfi'd, aſide I threw</l>
                  <l>My own affairs, and privately withdrew</l>
                  <l>Into my ſelf, in ſeaſon to begin</l>
                  <l>That undertaking which I now am in;</l>
                  <l>And whereto you, by theſe <hi>long lanes</hi> are led,</l>
                  <l>To ſignifie that I've conſidered</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> which to light I bring,</l>
                  <l>With good <hi>precautions,</hi> and examining.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>One <hi>afternoon,</hi> as on my couch I lay,</l>
                  <l>About the <hi>ev'ning twilight</hi> of the day,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>contemplation</hi> introduced there,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>mask,</hi> that might beſeem a <hi>theater;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And many grave <hi>ſpectators:</hi> for thereby</l>
                  <l>Was repreſented our late <hi>tragedy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From that time, when the <hi>Prologue</hi> did begin,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n to the very <hi>act,</hi> we now are in;</l>
                  <l>With each materiall circumſtance, which might,</l>
                  <l>Be uſefully preſented to my ſight,</l>
                  <l>Pertaining to this <hi>Nation,</hi> and to thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who <hi>are,</hi> or <hi>have been,</hi> thereto friends or foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It likewiſe drew a <hi>map</hi> before mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>Of all our paſt, and preſent miſeries,</l>
                  <l>With thoſe <hi>diſtractions,</hi> and thoſe <hi>contradictions.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich do prolong or multiply <hi>afflictions:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As alſo of each <hi>actor</hi> and his <hi>actions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Confuſedly wrapt up with their <hi>tranſactions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As they to me, and other men appear,</l>
                  <l>When we do look upon them in our fear;</l>
                  <l>Or as they paſſed by us day by day,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt we among the ſame confuſions lay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>mummery</hi> withdrew: and then me thought,</l>
                  <l>It back again, each <hi>part</hi> and <hi>actor</hi> brought,</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116012:27"/>
                  <l>Diſtinctly repreſented, ſo that I</l>
                  <l>Might perfectly diſcern with <hi>reaſons eye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What in themſelves they were; and that we had</l>
                  <l>Of many things a <hi>wrong conjecture</hi> made.</l>
                  <l>That ſome, which to our practiſe were commended,</l>
                  <l>Have to our ſhame, and our deſtruction tended:</l>
                  <l>That others, which we judged might deſtroy</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>intereſt;</hi> produc'd what we enjoy.</l>
                  <l>That wicked <hi>projects,</hi> other while brought forth</l>
                  <l>As good effects, as thoſe of <hi>reall worth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Though not without a woe, to them, by whom</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Offences,</hi> and <hi>prevarications</hi> come)</l>
                  <l>That ſome, which good appear'd, were nothing ſo,</l>
                  <l>That, others, making but an evill ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Were (if conſider'd ſimply) very good,</l>
                  <l>Or, better then they ſeem'd, if underſtood</l>
                  <l>According to the <hi>time,</hi> and preſent ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of theſe <hi>affairs,</hi> whereto they did relate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Curtain</hi> then was drawn aſide, that ſhew'd</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Table,</hi> whereon portraited I view'd</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Directory,</hi> teaching me the uſe</l>
                  <l>Of all that I had ſeen, with their produce:</l>
                  <l>Which could my memory, have brought away,</l>
                  <l>Had done this work (which I intend to day)</l>
                  <l>Much better, then this <hi>picking</hi> out again,</l>
                  <l>What their impreſſion left upon my <hi>brain.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A thouſand ſev'rall things (ſome, neither fit</l>
                  <l>For my expreſſion, nor in ſeaſon, yet</l>
                  <l>To be divulg'd) were brought as in <hi>proceſſion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before me, in an orderly <hi>progreſſion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometimes confuſedly, there paſſed by</l>
                  <l>Strange <hi>Apparitions,</hi> which away did fly,</l>
                  <l>E're I could well diſern them; or my <hi>thought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take notice, to what purpoſe they were brought.</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116012:28"/>
                  <l>Sometimes <hi>bright ſhinings</hi> from a light I had,</l>
                  <l>Which cheer'd my <hi>heart,</hi> and made my <hi>ſpirit</hi> glad.</l>
                  <l>Another while, a <hi>darkneſſe</hi> me ſurrounded,</l>
                  <l>Which, all my <hi>notions,</hi> for a time, confounded,</l>
                  <l>And ſadned ſo my <hi>ſpirit</hi> by privations,</l>
                  <l>That I well neer loſt all thoſe <hi>obſervations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which I had made ſometimes appear'd to me</l>
                  <l>Such things, as in our <hi>Antimasks</hi> we ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> and worthy laughing at;</l>
                  <l>Sometimes <hi>things terrible,</hi> and after that</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Appearances,</hi> which promiſed to ſome,</l>
                  <l>Much <hi>comfort, peace,</hi> and <hi>happineſſe to come;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo the <hi>Viſion</hi> vaniſh'd, and the <hi>day</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By that time to the <hi>night</hi> had given way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But by <hi>what repreſented</hi> thus hath been,</l>
                  <l>By well conſidering what I have ſeen;</l>
                  <l>(By <hi>ſpelling out,</hi> what every character</l>
                  <l>Held forth, and what things evidenced were</l>
                  <l>By <hi>readring all together</hi>) found hath bin</l>
                  <l>Where that <hi>great work</hi> muſt firſt of all begin,</l>
                  <l>Which may make up our <hi>breaches,</hi> when thereto</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves we ſettle, as we ought to do.</l>
                  <l>In brief, I ſaw, that in the <hi>ſettlement</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>conſtitution</hi> of this <hi>Parliament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Upon a juſt <hi>foundation</hi> laid with ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>A courſe of <hi>reſtauration</hi> might ſucceed;</l>
                  <l>And draw on by <hi>degrees,</hi> a means to bring</l>
                  <l>Into <hi>right order,</hi> ev'ry other thing</l>
                  <l>Conducing to our <hi>Weal;</hi> and if we take</l>
                  <l>That way whereof propoſall I ſhall make,</l>
                  <l>I dare adventure, if it do not thrive,</l>
                  <l>To loſe my head, or be inter'd alive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I have attain'd aſſurance (and without</l>
                  <l>So much as any ſhadow of a doubt</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116012:28"/>
                  <l>That by this <hi>Parliaments</hi> miſconſtitution</l>
                  <l>We are uncapable of that fruition</l>
                  <l>Which we expect; that for the moſt part thence</l>
                  <l>Proceed the cauſes of our indigence</l>
                  <l>And myſeries; and that 'tis naytheleſſe</l>
                  <l>The <hi>chief,</hi> or <hi>ſole means</hi> left of our redreſſe.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n this in being now, this which men ſeek</l>
                  <l>To bring into contempt, and to diſlike.</l>
                  <l>This, which they (juſtly too, in ſome reſpect)</l>
                  <l>Have laboured to make of no effect,</l>
                  <l>And to annihilate, as if thereby</l>
                  <l>(And thereby only) they ſhould perfectly</l>
                  <l>Injoy their full deſires, and be ſecur'd</l>
                  <l>From all the troubles hitherto indur'd.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n by this <hi>Parliament,</hi> God will effect</l>
                  <l>That future ſettlement which we expect,</l>
                  <l>If we too long delay not the purſuit</l>
                  <l>Of an impartiall rativall recruit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For though the body of it being made</l>
                  <l>Of many members, hath among them had</l>
                  <l>(And hath yet) overmany ſo corrupted</l>
                  <l>That they have not alone much interrupted:</l>
                  <l>The activeneſſe of thoſe that have been ſound,</l>
                  <l>But are oft likely alſo to confound</l>
                  <l>The whole at once, by ſeeking how to pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>luſts,</hi> or <hi>friends,</hi> or how themſelves to eaſe:</l>
                  <l>Yet by their faithfulneſs, who have been true</l>
                  <l>Unto their truſt, and active to purſue</l>
                  <l>The <hi>publike intereſt,</hi> redeem'd we are</l>
                  <l>From that captivity in which we were;</l>
                  <l>And many things enjoy of him eſteem</l>
                  <l>(Though by ſome wants, <hi>enjoyments</hi> leſſe do ſeem)</l>
                  <l>Whereof we had e're this been quite diſpoil'd,</l>
                  <l>If they in their endeavours had been foir'd.</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116012:29"/>
                  <l>It therefore were an Act of <hi>Tyranny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Of high injuſtice, and of cruelty)</l>
                  <l>To wrap up theſe, with thoſe that have miſdone,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſome fail, to have reſpect to none;</l>
                  <l>But caſt off all at once, and from us thruſt</l>
                  <l>With men unrighteous, thoſe that have been juſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For if we weigh things well, it is their praiſe,</l>
                  <l>That they have marched through uneven wayes,</l>
                  <l>(Oft, ill accommodated) and have long</l>
                  <l>Oppoſed without wearineſſe, a ſtrong</l>
                  <l>And cunning enemy; that they have bin</l>
                  <l>Aſſail'd by ſome without, and ſtob'd within</l>
                  <l>By <hi>boſome foes;</hi> that they were lamed too,</l>
                  <l>In their own <hi>limbs,</hi> yet forward ſtill did go</l>
                  <l>With perſeverance: and that alſo they</l>
                  <l>Stand for us in the gap, ev'n to this day;</l>
                  <l>It is their glory, rather then their blot,</l>
                  <l>Though their good purpoſe they accompliſh not.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is from theſe that we denominate</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Parliament;</hi> in them is lodg'd the fate</l>
                  <l>Of this <hi>Republike;</hi> yea, what e're it ſeem,</l>
                  <l>This, as I ſaid, is that which muſt redeem</l>
                  <l>Our late loſt honor; and if e're this ſhall</l>
                  <l>Diſſolved be, down all our <hi>Structures</hi> fall,</l>
                  <l>Not to be rais'd, without the coſt of more</l>
                  <l>Then hath been ſpent upon it heretofore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For what ſhould keep it up? can wiſe men think,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall uphold it, that it may not ſink,</l>
                  <l>Whom theſe depute? who while they do ſubſiſt,</l>
                  <l>Preſerve, with much care, their own intereſt?</l>
                  <l>Can any of us, reaſonably believe</l>
                  <l>The power which to their <hi>Subſtitutes</hi> theſe give,</l>
                  <l>When they themſelves are outed, ſhall be able</l>
                  <l>To keep up ſtrongly, that which is unſtable,</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116012:29"/>
                  <l>Untill a <hi>Phoenix,</hi> yet unhatch'd ariſe</l>
                  <l>Out of their aſhes, with renew'd ſupplies?</l>
                  <l>When, having far leſſe power, and leſſe eſteem,</l>
                  <l>(As being an extraction out of them</l>
                  <l>Who are prejudicated) they ſhall contend</l>
                  <l>With thoſe <hi>immergencies,</hi> that may aſcend?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, grant it poſſible, what way ſhall we</l>
                  <l>Contrive, whereby this power diſſolv'd may be</l>
                  <l>Without a <hi>force,</hi> that may indanger more</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>ſafety,</hi> then it hath done heretofore?</l>
                  <l>(Since by a Law, it was perpetuated</l>
                  <l>Which is not raſhly to be <hi>abrogated;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And which without inforcement, can by none</l>
                  <l>Repealed be, ſave by <hi>it ſelf</hi> alone?)</l>
                  <l>It were not rationall we ſhould petition</l>
                  <l>That they now ſitting (weighing their condition)</l>
                  <l>Diſſolve it ſhould, till they can be aſſured,</l>
                  <l>How they may for the future be ſecured,</l>
                  <l>For giving their <hi>intruſted power</hi> away,</l>
                  <l>To thoſe they know not; or, to ſuch as may,</l>
                  <l>Ruine both <hi>them,</hi> and thoſe too, for whoſe ſake,</l>
                  <l>They ſerv'd, that reaſonleſſe reſolve to make;</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſhould they leave to ſuch <hi>uncertainties,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And, to ſuch hazards, as might thence ariſe)</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> it were an Act unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>And, an unanſwerable breach of truſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Parliament, though (by and for our ſin)</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>vigorous actings</hi> have delayed bin,</l>
                  <l>Through thoſe <hi>obſtructions,</hi> which it long hath had,</l>
                  <l>And, is by many foul <hi>bespatterings</hi> made</l>
                  <l>Unacceptable; though, that it ſhould raign</l>
                  <l>O're them, the <hi>ſons of Belial,</hi> do diſdain:</l>
                  <l>Although, ſome alſo (without cauſe) have thought</l>
                  <l>That, to defame it, <hi>I my ſelf,</hi> have ſought</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116012:30"/>
                  <l>(Becauſe thereto miſunderſtandingly,</l>
                  <l>They ſuch <hi>invectives,</hi> and <hi>reproofs</hi> apply,</l>
                  <l>As were intended only againſt thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeming to be <hi>friends,</hi> were ſecret <hi>foes.</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Yet ſince it firſt begun (ev'n all along)</l>
                  <l>I have perceiv'd what <hi>works</hi> thereto belong,</l>
                  <l>And ever had a care how to prevent</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſcandall,</hi> by a plain diſtinguiſhment</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Doves</hi> from <hi>Crowes,</hi> and of mens <hi>private factions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>publike,</hi> and <hi>authorized tranſactions.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For as that man, who can nor hear, nor ſee,</l>
                  <l>And half whoſe limbs, corrupt and rotten be,</l>
                  <l>May poſſibly be all the means reſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>By which a <hi>noble houſe</hi> may be preſerv'd</l>
                  <l>From <hi>extirpation;</hi> ſo, how bad ſoe're</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Parliament</hi> may be, (or may appear)</l>
                  <l>I am aſſur'd, by many a circumſtance,</l>
                  <l>It is that means by which GOD will advance</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> unto that <hi>ſettlement,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which may accurſed <hi>Anarchy</hi> prevent,</l>
                  <l>If thoſe <hi>conditions</hi> be not long neglected,</l>
                  <l>Whereby our happineſs may be effected.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As heretofore, when <hi>Sarah</hi> was bereav'd</l>
                  <l>Of that which gave her hope to have conceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>She, naytheleſſe, obtain'd a lovely ſon,</l>
                  <l>In whom a <hi>num'rous Off-ſpring</hi> was begun:</l>
                  <l>And whence did ſpring that <hi>light,</hi> and that <hi>ſalvation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which is the happineſs of ev'ry Nation;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n ſo, when we had wanted many a year,</l>
                  <l>The likely <hi>Symptoms</hi> of enjoying here,</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>Parliament;</hi> yea when a ſtop</l>
                  <l>Was raiſed and proclaim'd, againſt the hope</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a mercy, when nought did appear</l>
                  <l>But that whereby diſpairs increaſed were:</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116012:30"/>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Tympanies</hi> had ſwoln our <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb,</l>
                  <l>And made it rather ſeem to be the <hi>Tomb</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>dead things</hi> only, then to quicken ought,</l>
                  <l>VVhich for our comfort could from thence be brought;</l>
                  <l>Lo, then, (and not before) it did conceive</l>
                  <l>A ſon of <hi>Conſolation,</hi> to revive</l>
                  <l>Our drooping hearts; and which, if <hi>faithleſneſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deprive us not of what we may poſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Will free us from all <hi>tyrants,</hi> and reſtore</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>rights</hi> which they uſurped heretofore:</l>
                  <l>And not reſtore our <hi>liberties</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>But propagate the bleſſing here begun,</l>
                  <l>Throughout the world, untill all other <hi>Nations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are freed from their <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> uſurpations.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before the <hi>ſons of Jacob</hi> entrance found</l>
                  <l>Into their <hi>promis'd Land,</hi> they had a round,</l>
                  <l>Or Progreſs to fulfill, and many years</l>
                  <l>They in the <hi>Deſarts</hi> were <hi>Probationers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By ſev'rall <hi>hardſhips,</hi> thereby to improve</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſeeds of faith,</hi> new ſown at their remove</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Aegypt;</hi> and by <hi>ſigns</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> ſhown)</l>
                  <l>To make unto themſelves their frailty known.</l>
                  <l>But they at each reſtraining of their luſt,</l>
                  <l>Brake forth into repinings and diſtruſt;</l>
                  <l>Yea into flat <hi>rebellions,</hi> into rearing</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Idols</hi> (when his Law GOD was preparing)</l>
                  <l>Into a wicked cauſleſſe murmuring</l>
                  <l>Againſt the means of their delivering</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Aegypts</hi> triall; and into wiſhes vain</l>
                  <l>That they might thither back return again.</l>
                  <l>For which of many hundred thouſands none</l>
                  <l>Enjoy'd the <hi>promis'd rest,</hi> but two alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And we are juſt like them; yea, we have done</l>
                  <l>Since God, to bring us from our <hi>thrall</hi> begun,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:116012:31"/>
                  <l>The very ſame things in the <hi>wilderneſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of our <hi>Probation;</hi> and our carkaſſes</l>
                  <l>Shall there be left, unleſs we do betimes</l>
                  <l>Make an <hi>attunement,</hi> for our paſſed crimes;</l>
                  <l>And with unfainedneſs that <hi>courſe</hi> purſue</l>
                  <l>Which leads unto the reſt, that is in view.</l>
                  <l>So ſhall our Leaders, likewiſe, who comply</l>
                  <l>With ſuch <hi>tranſgreſſers,</hi> and unſanctifie</l>
                  <l>Their power: ſo ſhall, moreover, thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who with our <hi>Dathans,</hi> and <hi>Abirams</hi> cloſe</l>
                  <l>In their conſpiracies, and quite from all</l>
                  <l>Their likely hopes, and preſent glory fall.</l>
                  <l>For on <hi>conditions,</hi> (as King <hi>John</hi> had</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Throne</hi>) the peoples heads, they have been made,</l>
                  <l>And if they ſhall from thoſe conditions ſwerve,</l>
                  <l>They muſt expect the portion they deſerve.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let them endeavour, therefore, how they may</l>
                  <l>Remove that <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>jealouſie</hi> away</l>
                  <l>Which doth poſſeſſe the people, and withdraws</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>good affections,</hi> with apparent cauſe:</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>thoſe,</hi> (<hi>ev'n thoſe, who have among the reſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Been leaſt to blame, and have deſerved beſt</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Conſider, that by ſuch as careleſſe are</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe great <hi>burthens,</hi> which they ſeem to bear,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>weight</hi> increaſeth, and, that they ſo faſt</l>
                  <l>Decreaſe, on whom their weightineſs is caſt,</l>
                  <l>As will e're long o're whelm them, if with ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>They do not to ſome remedy proceed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let them take notice, that the people rage</l>
                  <l>At their <hi>delayes,</hi> as likely to ingage</l>
                  <l>In ſome <hi>diſorderly reſolve,</hi> unleſs</l>
                  <l>They ſee that follow'd with more ſeriouſneſs</l>
                  <l>Which they deſire; either a <hi>Parl'ament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>New made, or ſomewhat that's equivalent:</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116012:31"/>
                  <l>For thereby, they conceive, (and that thereby</l>
                  <l>Alone) their <hi>ſufferings</hi> may have remedy.</l>
                  <l>And ſomewhat to that end (although not ſo</l>
                  <l>As moſt would have it) may be ſit to do.</l>
                  <l>Yea, if I have not miſadviſed bin,</l>
                  <l>Our cure muſt with the <hi>Parliament</hi> begin.</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt ye therefore, to promote the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Leſt ye partake with ſinners in their ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There is a courſe, whereby without diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>danger,</hi> you may bring that <hi>work</hi> to paſs,</l>
                  <l>And free your ſelves from that great coſt and pain,</l>
                  <l>Which without <hi>thanks,</hi> or <hi>profit</hi> you ſuſtain;</l>
                  <l>Afflicting others too, by thoſe <hi>confuſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which are increaſt by your irreſolutions.</l>
                  <l>Untill a better, therefore ſhall appear,</l>
                  <l>Be pleaſed that <hi>expediment</hi> to hear,</l>
                  <l>And, if of thoſe <hi>preventions,</hi> or that <hi>good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It promiſeth, you find a likelyhood,</l>
                  <l>Take heed, that no ſelf-intereſt, divert</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Approbation,</hi> whereunto your heart</l>
                  <l>Inclineth you; for God will find it out,</l>
                  <l>And croſs the <hi>counter-work</hi> you go about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In <hi>England,</hi> and in <hi>Wales,</hi> there is a <hi>Shire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ev'ry <hi>week</hi> that's numbred in the year.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>twelve,</hi> according to the <hi>moneths</hi> divide</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Counties,</hi> with their perſons qualifi'd</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> proportioning</l>
                  <l>As neer as may be, to an equalling</l>
                  <l>The <hi>number</hi> of the <hi>whole,</hi> ſo, or ſo many</l>
                  <l>Unto each <hi>moneth,</hi> without omitting any.</l>
                  <l>Aſcertain then, the <hi>moneth</hi> and <hi>day,</hi> wherein</l>
                  <l>Each <hi>twelfth part</hi> an <hi>election</hi> ſhall begin;</l>
                  <l>(The <hi>middle of the week,</hi> appearing beſt</l>
                  <l>As being furtheſt from the day of <hi>reſt</hi>)</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116012:32"/>
                  <l>On each firſt <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> of each moneth, let thoſe</l>
                  <l>By whom their <hi>Deputies</hi> are to be choſe,</l>
                  <l>Reſpectively convene in ev'ry Shire,</l>
                  <l>Upon that <hi>moneth,</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday</hi> ev'ry year,</l>
                  <l>Which is to them aſſign'd; and having choſen,</l>
                  <l>(At <hi>moneths</hi> end) let each <hi>twelfth part,</hi> of the dozen,</l>
                  <l>Send up their <hi>choſen men,</hi> to repreſent</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Shires</hi> and <hi>Boroughs</hi> in the <hi>Parliament:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And on that very day, in which they come,</l>
                  <l>Let all their <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> give them room.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus one <hi>moneth</hi> ſome; and <hi>moneth</hi> by <hi>moneth</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</l>
                  <l>Let each <hi>twelfth part,</hi> ſtill orderly perſever</l>
                  <l>To take a <hi>turn,</hi> till ev'ry ſhare hath had</l>
                  <l>A <hi>moneth</hi> in ev'ry year; and having made</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>choice,</hi> let them ſtill <hi>enter</hi> and <hi>withdraw</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Succeſſively, by a <hi>perpetuall Law,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No man a <hi>place of truſt,</hi> ſupplying there,</l>
                  <l>At one <hi>election,</hi> longer then one year.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus, as the <hi>Thames,</hi> doth ſtill continue <hi>one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And is the ſelf-ſame river, though there run</l>
                  <l>A new ſupply of waters ev'ry day</l>
                  <l>Along the channell, ſo continue may</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Parliament,</hi> by annuall ſupply,</l>
                  <l>To be the ſelf-ſame everlaſtingly,</l>
                  <l>With very little charge or moleſtation</l>
                  <l>To thoſe who <hi>chuſe,</hi> or repreſent the <hi>Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus may this <hi>Parliament,</hi> be both together</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Succeſſive,</hi> and perpetuall; yet neither</l>
                  <l>Enjoying ſuch a <hi>perpetuity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As can occaſion future <hi>tyranny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or preſent <hi>grievances;</hi> not that <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which may bring danger by an <hi>intermiſſion:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But make that <hi>conſtitution,</hi> which will add</l>
                  <l>All power, which may from both of them be had,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:116012:32"/>
                  <l>Either to compaſs, what good men affect;</l>
                  <l>Or to prevent the miſchiefs they ſuſpect,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What I intend may plainly be conceiv'd;</l>
                  <l>And to that end, ſome things may be contriv'd</l>
                  <l>Much better, if your wiſdome ſhall refine</l>
                  <l>The rudeneſs of my profered deſign;</l>
                  <l>And by authority, ſome <hi>rules</hi> provide</l>
                  <l>Whereby th' <hi>elected</hi> may be qualifi'd;</l>
                  <l>And their <hi>Electors</hi> too; for 'twere unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>In things of this <hi>concernment,</hi> thoſe to truſt</l>
                  <l>Who have diſturb'd our <hi>Peace,</hi> untill a time</l>
                  <l>For their <hi>Probation</hi> be allotted them:</l>
                  <l>And till they likewiſe, by ſome good deſert,</l>
                  <l>Make manifeſt a <hi>reconciled heart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ateſted, and approved by thoſe <hi>Judges,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ſhall ſuſpend their former <hi>priviledges.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince, ev'n they who are the beſt affected</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Publike welfare,</hi> often have elected</l>
                  <l>Such as deceive their hopes; ſince ther's no eye</l>
                  <l>But GODS, that ſees the hearts hypocriſic:</l>
                  <l>Since it appeareth in the beſt <hi>Record,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Ev'n in the <hi>volumes</hi> of the <hi>ſacred Word</hi>)</l>
                  <l>That <hi>lots</hi> were needfull in the choice of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>On whom they did a <hi>Supreme Truſt</hi> impoſe:</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſince, ev'n when the pureſt <hi>Congregation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In all the world, had with deliberation,</l>
                  <l>(And from among the moſt approved men,</l>
                  <l>Which to their knowledge liv'd among them then)</l>
                  <l>Elected <hi>two;</hi> a <hi>lot</hi> was alſo caſt,</l>
                  <l>That GODS <hi>Election</hi> might on theirs be plac'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſend forth him, who was to be employ'd</l>
                  <l>In executing of the place then void:</l>
                  <l>Since alſo GODS <hi>Election,</hi> joyn'd with our,</l>
                  <l>May <hi>peradventure</hi> on the <hi>Elected</hi> pour</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:116012:33"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>New gifts;</hi> ſince we by doubtleſſe warranty</l>
                  <l>May with that antient <hi>Preſident</hi> comply:</l>
                  <l>Since it will probably give good content</l>
                  <l>To prudent men, and may oft times prevent</l>
                  <l>The <hi>choice</hi> of thoſe, whom for ſiniſter ends,</l>
                  <l>A numerous <hi>corrupted Party</hi> ſends:</l>
                  <l>Why may not? nay, why ſhould not <hi>two</hi> be choſe</l>
                  <l>For ev'ry place that's void, and <hi>one</hi> of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Be ſent by <hi>lot?</hi> that GOD may have a <hi>voice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And joyn with men in making up their <hi>choice?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Since they, who muſt this <hi>Nation</hi> repreſent</l>
                  <l>Are GODS <hi>Vicegerents</hi> in the Government,</l>
                  <l>As well as our <hi>Truſtees?</hi> who would not more</l>
                  <l>Conſide in ſuch a <hi>choice,</hi> then heretofore</l>
                  <l>They did in others? or, then they will do</l>
                  <l>In them, who ſhall not now be <hi>choſen</hi> ſo?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why was it not? why ſhould it not be thus,</l>
                  <l>If this the <hi>Kingdome</hi> be of GOD WITH US?</l>
                  <l>But that <hi>ſelf-ſeekers</hi> find, were this admitted,</l>
                  <l>They by <hi>reputed fools,</hi> ſhould be out-witted?</l>
                  <l>And get no <hi>Jnlet,</hi> others to devoure</l>
                  <l>Hereafter, by an evill gotten power?</l>
                  <l>Yea, wherefore hath the <hi>lot</hi> been from among</l>
                  <l>All our <hi>Elections</hi> kept away ſo long,</l>
                  <l>But that <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and <hi>Intruders</hi> know</l>
                  <l>It would their <hi>Kingdomes</hi> wholly overthrow;</l>
                  <l>Make them afraid, that CHRIST would raign indeed</l>
                  <l>Among us, (as they ſometimes hear and read)</l>
                  <l>And that they ſhould hereafter never come</l>
                  <l>To revel (as they have done) in his room:</l>
                  <l>Nor will they, doubtleſs, if this take effect,</l>
                  <l>Except it be our failings to correct;</l>
                  <l>When GOD ſhall by permiſſion for our ſin,</l>
                  <l>Reject the <hi>lot,</hi> and let a <hi>Knave</hi> come in.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:116012:33"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>If therefore ſome <hi>Previſion</hi> might be made,</l>
                  <l>That we ſhould <hi>lots</hi> to our <hi>Elections</hi> add,</l>
                  <l>A great ſecurity would thence redound,</l>
                  <l>And much contentment therein might be found.</l>
                  <l>Moreover, as an <hi>out-work</hi> pertinent</l>
                  <l>Remiſſeneſs in <hi>Electers</hi> to prevent,</l>
                  <l>(Upon whoſe due performance much depends,</l>
                  <l>Which to the <hi>publike woe,</hi> or <hi>welfare</hi> tends)</l>
                  <l>It were not labour loſt, if whenſoe're</l>
                  <l>To execute that duty we appear,</l>
                  <l>Some ſhort ſpeech might be made, or <hi>cautions read,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereby it ſhould be offred to our heed,</l>
                  <l>How much it will concern us, to take care</l>
                  <l>What <hi>choice</hi> we make, and what the danger; are</l>
                  <l>Which may enſue; leſt for ſiniſter ends,</l>
                  <l>(For fear of <hi>great men,</hi> or to pleaſe our <hi>friends</hi>)</l>
                  <l>We may diſplace our <hi>trust,</hi> and caſt away</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves, and all, for ever, in one day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To which intent, our <hi>Orator</hi> ſhould ſhow</l>
                  <l>What <hi>trust</hi> it is, which we that day beſtow:</l>
                  <l>What <hi>benefits</hi> may gen'rally ariſe</l>
                  <l>By chuſing men <hi>couragious, honest, wiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And fearing GOD; what <hi>perills</hi> will enſue</l>
                  <l>(Which by forepaſt <hi>examples</hi> he may ſhew)</l>
                  <l>If <hi>cowards, fools, ungodly</hi> men, and <hi>vitious,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or to the <hi>preſent Government</hi> pernitious</l>
                  <l>Elected be; he likewiſe may declare</l>
                  <l>How <hi>qualifi'd</hi> ſuch perſons ſhould appear,</l>
                  <l>And warn them, that they never do unhallow</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>choice,</hi> with any ſuch as theſe that follow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men over-talkative, and loving much</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To hear themſelves ſpeak;</hi> for not many ſuch</l>
                  <l>Can keep or give good <hi>counſell;</hi> and they'l prate</l>
                  <l>Much precious time away, in vain debate.</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:116012:34"/>
                  <l>Your <hi>common Gameſters:</hi> for, they are unjuſt</l>
                  <l>Unto themſelves, and them we ſhould not truſt</l>
                  <l>With other mens <hi>eſtates,</hi> who have been known</l>
                  <l>To loſe, or hazard, deſperately their own.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men to their pleaſure overmuch addicted,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>Publike works,</hi> will be by theſe neglected.</l>
                  <l>Such as apparently are <hi>Avaritious,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or of <hi>Promotion greedily ambitions:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For if their ends thereby acquire they may,</l>
                  <l>Theſe may be hir'd, their <hi>Country</hi> to betray.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such as indulge their lust,</hi> and famed are</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ju their uncleanneſſes to perſevere;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For they will leave their Charge, to pleaſe their whore,</l>
                  <l>And ſhame their fellows, if they do no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of <hi>irreligious perſons</hi> make no choice,</l>
                  <l>For theſe will very ſeldome give their <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But in the <hi>Negative,</hi> to any motion.</l>
                  <l>That may be for advancement of <hi>Devotion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chuſe none who are defam'd in any kind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As being vitious;</hi> for theſe means will find</l>
                  <l>To hinder all <hi>enactings,</hi> which reſtrain</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ill manners;</hi> or to <hi>ſober life</hi> pertain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elect</hi> not <hi>children:</hi> for it is unfit</l>
                  <l>That in our <hi>Supreme Counſell</hi> they ſhould ſit,</l>
                  <l>To Vote in <hi>Grand Affairs,</hi> whom <hi>Law</hi> reſtrains</l>
                  <l>From managing, what to <hi>themſelves</hi> pertains.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chuſe none,</hi> who are obſerved to withhold,</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>long due debts, when they diſcharge them could;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>outlaw'd perſons;</hi> for, unfit are they</l>
                  <l>To make our <hi>Lawes,</hi> who will not <hi>Lawes</hi> obey.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chuſe none, who ſhall ſolicite, or</hi> propoſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That they for your Law makers may be choſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And their <hi>Electors,</hi> by the old abuſe,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>feaſting, wine,</hi> and <hi>banquetings</hi> ſeduce:)</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116012:34"/>
                  <l>For they, who ſhall uncall'd, themſelves advance</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>great work,</hi> have much more <hi>arrogance</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then <hi>worth;</hi> and it is alſo ten to one,</l>
                  <l>They for themſelves, have ſomething to be done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And laſtly, take good heed, that none get in</l>
                  <l>By your <hi>Elections,</hi> who have active bin</l>
                  <l>Againſt this <hi>State,</hi> till you, of them have had</l>
                  <l>Good proof, whereby ſecure you may be made:</l>
                  <l>For he that hath into ſubjection brought,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Thief,</hi> who on the way, to rob him ſought,</l>
                  <l>And ſtraight way truſts him, with his <hi>ſword</hi> and <hi>horſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Takes not a very ſafe, or prudent courſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This being done, (as in preceding ages)</l>
                  <l>Let thoſe who are <hi>Elected</hi> have their wages</l>
                  <l>Well paid, and rendered proportionable</l>
                  <l>To what the times require, to make them able</l>
                  <l>To ſerve their Country in the <hi>Parliament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Without their private coſt or detriment:</l>
                  <l>For both our <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> requires,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Labourers</hi> ſhould be allow'd their hires:</l>
                  <l>Yea, 'tis a kind of <hi>bribery,</hi> in thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who offer, without <hi>wages</hi> to be choſe;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Boroughs,</hi> which unable ſeem to beare</l>
                  <l>That <hi>charge,</hi> not worth the repreſenting are.</l>
                  <l>Beſide, their <hi>choice,</hi> is (for the moſt part) made</l>
                  <l>By ſome <hi>Malignant Stewards;</hi> or, or'e aw'd</l>
                  <l>By miſaffected <hi>Landlords,</hi> to the wrong</l>
                  <l>Of what to them, with others doth belong:</l>
                  <l>And their <hi>objections</hi> are but <hi>cavillings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ſhall alledge, that theſe <hi>eſt abliſhings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Infringe their <hi>Antient Right:</hi> for, be it known,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Commonwealth</hi> no <hi>priviledge</hi> can own</l>
                  <l>Deſtructive to it <hi>ſelf:</hi> much rather, we,</l>
                  <l>Who now, by <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> teinveſted be</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:116012:35"/>
                  <l>With what was loſt, are bound to ſettle it,</l>
                  <l>Not as our foes wiſh, but as may befit</l>
                  <l>The preſent, and the future preſervation</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſafety, peace,</hi> and <hi>freedome</hi> to this <hi>Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moreover, as upon the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It was the cuſtome, in preceding years,</l>
                  <l>That there the <hi>Sages of the Law,</hi> attended;</l>
                  <l>To whoſe debate ſuch <hi>points</hi> were recommended,</l>
                  <l>As to the Law related; ſo, let ſome</l>
                  <l>Selected be, and ſummoned to come</l>
                  <l>To whom each matter queſtioned relates,</l>
                  <l>To be advis'd withall, in their <hi>debates,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As needfull it ſhall ſeem; whether the cauſe</l>
                  <l>In <hi>controverſie</hi> ſhall concern the <hi>Laws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>War, Merchandize,</hi> or whatſoever may</l>
                  <l>Require their beſt experience on the day</l>
                  <l>Thereto aſſign'd: that ev'ry work begun</l>
                  <l>May by it proper <hi>inſtrument</hi> be done.</l>
                  <l>Which will prevent much <hi>doing,</hi> and <hi>undoing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And make <hi>now comers,</hi> in ſhort time, as knowing,</l>
                  <l>As they that have ſate long, and finiſh more</l>
                  <l>In <hi>three weeks,</hi> then in <hi>three moneths</hi> heretofore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>outworks,</hi> will much ſtrengthen, and ſecure</l>
                  <l>The <hi>works within:</hi> yet that they may endure</l>
                  <l>All ſieges, underminings, and ſcaladoes,</l>
                  <l>Battries, aſſaults, and ſtormings, with Granadoes,</l>
                  <l>By ſoes without, and treacheries within,</l>
                  <l>To build a <hi>Cittadell,</hi> let us begin</l>
                  <l>Upon ſome <hi>Fundamentalls;</hi> and provide</l>
                  <l>They may for ever, unrepeal'd abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let it inviolably be decreed,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Cities, Shires,</hi> and <hi>Boroughs</hi> do proceed</l>
                  <l>Once ev'ry year, upon the time aſſign'd,</l>
                  <l>(On penalty of being deeply fin'd)</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:116012:35"/>
                  <l>To make <hi>Elections;</hi> that we never may</l>
                  <l>For time to come, be headleſs for one day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let it be <hi>overlaſting baniſhment</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To him, who ſhall to change this <hi>Government</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From being a <hi>Republike,</hi> motion make:</l>
                  <l>And to act further if he undertake,</l>
                  <l>Let it be death, with totall confiſcation</l>
                  <l>Of his <hi>eſtate,</hi> without commiſeration;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs the great Diſpoſer of all things,</l>
                  <l>(Who, as he liſts, ſets up and pulls down Kings)</l>
                  <l>Shall thereto by a conquering <hi>power</hi> compell;</l>
                  <l>And, not to do it then, were to rebell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoever with the <hi>publike Treaſury</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall ſtand intruſted; and doth knowingly</l>
                  <l>Defraud the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> or ſhall purloine,</l>
                  <l>(Whether it be in <hi>goods,</hi> or <hi>ready Coyne</hi>)</l>
                  <l>The worth of <hi>twenty ounces in pure plate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let it be loſs of <hi>life,</hi> and of <hi>eſtate.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoever this <hi>Republike</hi> ſhall betray</l>
                  <l>Maliciouſly, or for advance or pay,</l>
                  <l>Reſigne his <hi>Truſt;</hi> or cowardly give up</l>
                  <l>What he had means to keep, or likely hope;</l>
                  <l>Let it (when prov'd) be <hi>death without reprieving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or any hope of temporall forgiving.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoever ſhall from any <hi>foraigne State,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Prince,</hi> take penſion; or negotiate</l>
                  <l>With them, or with their <hi>Agents,</hi> when they are</l>
                  <l>With us in <hi>Treaties,</hi> or in open war,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>State affairs,</hi> unleſs the <hi>State</hi> gives leave;</l>
                  <l>Let him, without a <hi>pardon,</hi> death receive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Above a <hi>moneth</hi> together ſuffer none</l>
                  <l>To ſit hereafter in the <hi>Speakers</hi> throne,</l>
                  <l>On ſome great penalty: Becauſe thereby</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>publike wrongs,</hi> and <hi>private injuries</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:116012:36"/>
                  <l>May be occaſioned. Impoſe the like</l>
                  <l>On him that ſhall abſent himſelf one week</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Parliament,</hi> without a good cauſe ſhown;</l>
                  <l>Or, that without leave ſhall depart the Town.</l>
                  <l>Let ſome <hi>appearance</hi> every day be made,</l>
                  <l>That this <hi>great Body</hi> never want a <hi>Head</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That's viſible; and to prevent what may,</l>
                  <l>Unthought upon, befall us in a day.</l>
                  <l>Yea, on the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> for an houre or two,</l>
                  <l>Convene; for, 'tis a <hi>Sabboth-work</hi> you do:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Venice,</hi> hath by long experiment</l>
                  <l>Found, that this Caution may be pertinent;</l>
                  <l>Nor will it over-burthenſome appear,</l>
                  <l>When they are to continue but one year.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let none in <hi>Parliament</hi> have toleration</l>
                  <l>To mention ought to their <hi>diſreputation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who abſent are; except they undertake</l>
                  <l>Of what they ſhall aver good proof to make,</l>
                  <l>On pain of an <hi>expulſion;</hi> or, permit</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Intimation,</hi> likely to beget</l>
                  <l>A miſconjecture, to the injury</l>
                  <l>Of him, that is not preſent to reply:</l>
                  <l>But let th' <hi>Accuſers</hi> and their <hi>Accuſations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be known, that thoſe may have due vindications</l>
                  <l>Who are traduc'd; For, no man ſhould enjoy</l>
                  <l>A <hi>priviledge,</hi> his neighbour to deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>Moreover, leſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> become</l>
                  <l>(By multiplying Suits) more burthenſome</l>
                  <l>Then all thoſe other <hi>Courts,</hi> of whoſe oppreſſions</l>
                  <l>We have complain'd, (and render our conditions</l>
                  <l>Leſs curable) let it admit no Cauſe</l>
                  <l>But ſuch as hath no remedy by Lawes</l>
                  <l>In force; or, for a <hi>non-fruition</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> by their <hi>partiall execution.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:116012:36"/>
                  <l>For, by removing of ſuch <hi>grievances,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to provide againſt immergencies</l>
                  <l>Which may occurr (both in affairs <hi>abroad,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And here at <hi>home</hi>) they will have ſtill their load.</l>
                  <l>If not: the being of a <hi>Parliament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus conſtituted, doubtleſs, will prevent</l>
                  <l>So many miſchiefs, that it will return</l>
                  <l>Large recompences for all charges born.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let it <hi>expulſion</hi> be from thence, for ever,</l>
                  <l>With ſome great <hi>mulct,</hi> for any whoſoever,</l>
                  <l>That, as a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall ſit two years together; yea, though ſent.</l>
                  <l>And, let no <hi>Lawyers</hi> practiſe for a Fee,</l>
                  <l>Or plead, whil'ſt of the <hi>Parliament</hi> they be:</l>
                  <l>Or any, who there ſiteth as a <hi>Peer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be <hi>Iudge</hi> of any <hi>ſupreme Court</hi> that yeer;</l>
                  <l>Or, during that <hi>imployment,</hi> execute</l>
                  <l>A Place, permitting not a <hi>Substitute;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, in <hi>Appeals,</hi> none may infringe the <hi>Lawes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By being <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Partie</hi> in one Cauſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, that to all men, <hi>juſtice</hi> may be done,</l>
                  <l>Among your <hi>Fundamentalls</hi> make this <hi>one;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That whatſoever ſhall be taken from</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One, few,</hi> or <hi>many</hi> (through all times to come)</l>
                  <l>In <hi>publike wants,</hi> and <hi>dangers,</hi> be repaid</l>
                  <l>By <hi>equall Taxes,</hi> generally laid:</l>
                  <l>And, that they ſhall not <hi>make,</hi> or <hi>abrogate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Law,</hi> diminiſhing one mans eſtate</l>
                  <l>More then anothers, without recompence,</l>
                  <l>On whatſoe're occaſion or pretence.</l>
                  <l>Yea, let all mens eſtates reduced be</l>
                  <l>To leſſe then <hi>forty ſhillings, yearly Fee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rather then <hi>friend</hi> or <hi>foe,</hi> ſhould juſtly ſay,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>publike faith</hi> were broken, any way.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:116012:37"/>
                  <l>Which would inrich us, and <hi>innoble</hi> more</l>
                  <l>Then, if our <hi>hills of chalk,</hi> were <hi>ſilver o're;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>ſand</hi> pure <hi>gold;</hi> our <hi>pebles, pearls</hi> of <hi>price,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>fields</hi> as fruitfull as old <hi>Paradiſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ev'ry <hi>ſon,</hi> which forth each <hi>mother</hi> brings,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Lord,</hi> and all their Fathers <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then to prevent, the drawing thoſe together,</l>
                  <l>Who, for <hi>by-ends,</hi> would fortifie each other;</l>
                  <l>Let him that place in <hi>Parl'ament</hi> ſupplies,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall by <hi>letter, word,</hi> or otherwiſe,</l>
                  <l>Either <hi>contrive, ſolicite,</hi> or <hi>propoſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Another, during that time, to be choſe,</l>
                  <l>Be from his <hi>Truſt,</hi> exiled with diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Never to be admitted, to that place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, that all <hi>Fundamentalls</hi> ratifi'd</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Parl'ament,</hi> for ever may abide</l>
                  <l>Inviolated; let no man be ſent</l>
                  <l>A <hi>City, Town,</hi> or <hi>Shire,</hi> to repreſent,</l>
                  <l>Till by <hi>Indenture,</hi> under hand and ſeal,</l>
                  <l>He ſtand ingaged to the <hi>Common-weal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And his <hi>Electors,</hi> that by no endeavour,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall <hi>repeal,</hi> or any way for ever</l>
                  <l>Weaken theſe <hi>Fundamentalls;</hi> but aſſay,</l>
                  <l>At all times, to inlarge them what he may:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Parl'aments</hi> (as heretofore our <hi>Kings</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Are but <hi>Truſtees;</hi> and therefore in ſuch things,</l>
                  <l>As to the publike damage may redound,</l>
                  <l>As well as they, ſhold Act within ſome bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By theſe <hi>proviſions,</hi> (with ſome other ſuch</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Fundamentalls,</hi> we might very much</l>
                  <l>Advantage this <hi>Republike;</hi> and as far</l>
                  <l>As <hi>humane induſtries</hi> enabled are,</l>
                  <l>(To promiſe <hi>ſafety and eſtabliſhment</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Secure from change the <hi>preſent Government,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116012:37"/>
                  <l>Till men may dry-ſhod walk upon the ſand,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Deal,</hi> and <hi>Dover,</hi> Cliffs to <hi>Callis</hi> ſtrand;</l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>Penmin Maure,</hi> be ſet on <hi>Snow-down</hi> hills,</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Time</hi> unto their <hi>ſprings,</hi> turns back the <hi>rills.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This,</hi> would be like the <hi>river,</hi> wherewithall</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Tyrant Queller,</hi> cleans'd th' <hi>Augean ſtall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(As <hi>Poets</hi> faign) and waſh away that ſoil,</l>
                  <l>And bloud, and filth, which doth our beauty ſpoil.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>theſe means,</hi> we might both in one, contrive</l>
                  <l>A true <hi>ſucceſſive Repreſentative,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Compleated in a ſafe <hi>eſtabliſhment,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ever, of the ſelf-ſame <hi>Parl'ament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Producing all their juſt deſires together,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeek the <hi>one,</hi> or who deſire the <hi>other;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with prevention of all harms, that may</l>
                  <l>Be fear'd, by th' one or other way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By <hi>theſe means,</hi> we ſhall never be without</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Supreme power,</hi> or live in any doubt</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>harmfull change,</hi> if wiſely we purſue</l>
                  <l>This <hi>courſe;</hi> and to <hi>our ſelves</hi> continue true.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>theſe means,</hi> there will ſtill be an <hi>appearance</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sufficient, to keep up a perſeverance,</l>
                  <l>In all <hi>great undertakings,</hi> with due order,</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch quick diſpatch, the ſuits to further</l>
                  <l>Of men oppreſt; that, they may hope to ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>plaints</hi> determin'd, which yet endleſs be;</l>
                  <l>And never will have end, till <hi>wit</hi> or <hi>force,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reduce us unto this, or ſome ſuch <hi>courſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By <hi>this expedient,</hi> they that are in <hi>place</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At preſent, may reſign without <hi>diſgrace</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Truſt</hi> they have, to take a while their eaſe,</l>
                  <l>(Or follow their affairs, as they ſhall pleaſe)</l>
                  <l>And after <hi>one year,</hi> back perhaps return</l>
                  <l>To reaſſume the burthens they have born.</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:116012:38"/>
                  <l>Hereby a likely means will be contriv'd</l>
                  <l>Of that <hi>ſecurity,</hi> which is deriv'd</l>
                  <l>From <hi>many Counſellors:</hi> and, diſtribution</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>burthens,</hi> will make eaſie execution;</l>
                  <l>More quick, yea, and more cheap diſpatches too,</l>
                  <l>For thoſe, who ſhall have ought with them to do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By <hi>theſe means,</hi> if, a <hi>worthleſſe Member</hi> come</l>
                  <l>Among our <hi>Worthies,</hi> to ſupply a room,</l>
                  <l>His heart may changed be; whereas, now, they</l>
                  <l>Who came in honeſt, are oft drawn away</l>
                  <l>From their firſt <hi>Principles,</hi> with them to cloſe,</l>
                  <l>Who, mean to gain, what e're the <hi>Publike</hi> loſe:</l>
                  <l>Or, at the worſt, he muſt from thence be gone</l>
                  <l>Before much <hi>miſchief,</hi> can by him be done.</l>
                  <l>And, ſuch as do confederate and plot</l>
                  <l>That, for themſelves, advantage may be got,</l>
                  <l>(Though to their <hi>Countryes</hi> loſs, and <hi>neighbors</hi> wrong)</l>
                  <l>Shall want the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>means,</hi> which doth belong</l>
                  <l>To ſuch <hi>contrivements,</hi> as are frequent now,</l>
                  <l>When, moſt, each others <hi>minds,</hi> and <hi>intereſts</hi> know:</l>
                  <l>For, by <hi>new Parties,</hi> monethly, coming in,</l>
                  <l>They'l <hi>break,</hi> as faſt as they to <hi>knit</hi> begin;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>Gins,</hi> which heretofore effects have took</l>
                  <l>By <hi>kindred</hi> and <hi>alliance,</hi> will be <hi>broke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By <hi>theſe means,</hi> they, who do command, to day,</l>
                  <l>Shall learn again to <hi>morrow,</hi> to <hi>obey.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Many, ſhall be encourag'd to enable</l>
                  <l>Themſelves, in publike, to be ſerviceable;</l>
                  <l>And, in few years, ſome thouſands more then now,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>common intereſt,</hi> will learn to know;</l>
                  <l>And, how they may advance it, when they come</l>
                  <l>From that <hi>grand School,</hi> to live again, at home;</l>
                  <l>And, think themſelves, obliged, ev'ry where,</l>
                  <l>To further it, as well as ſitting there.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116012:38"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>By <hi>this means,</hi> ev'ry man, within his <hi>Orb</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall be reſtrain'd; and none have power to curb</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Supreme authority;</hi> or, to aſpire</l>
                  <l>By his ambition to a <hi>Station</hi> higher</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall be <hi>ſafe</hi> to all, and judged fit</l>
                  <l>For this <hi>free State,</hi> with prudence to admit:</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall the <hi>da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ingſt tyrant</hi> in the land</l>
                  <l>Preſume to move a <hi>tongu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> or lift a <hi>hand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Againſt that power; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>plot, vent,</hi> or <hi>concceal</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ought which may damnifie this <hi>Common-weal.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, by this <hi>means,</hi> we calmly ſhall reduce</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Parl'ament,</hi> unto it genuine uſe,</l>
                  <l>Without advent'ring what may intervene</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Intervalls;</hi> and, what hath feared been</l>
                  <l>(Not without cauſe) by hazarding to call</l>
                  <l>A <hi>new one;</hi> or, by an <hi>additionall</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Supply</hi> to <hi>this;</hi> as now <hi>affairs</hi> relate</l>
                  <l>To home <hi>deſigns,</hi> and <hi>our next neighbring State:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, if we fail in any <hi>circumſtance,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here mentioned, we never ſhall advance</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Publike intereſt</hi> to that effect,</l>
                  <l>Which by this <hi>Parliament</hi> we might expect;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſcape that <hi>tyranny,</hi> which is deſign'd</l>
                  <l>By <hi>thoſe,</hi> who are contrarily inclin'd:</l>
                  <l>For, they that would be <hi>tyrants</hi> (knowing thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who did the <hi>Regall tyranny</hi> oppoſe</l>
                  <l>Still zealous, for the <hi>peoples liberty</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Will to effect their purpoſes comply</l>
                  <l>With any party; and, then, by <hi>diſplacing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>diſenabling,</hi> or els by <hi>diſgracing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>well-affected,</hi> at laſt, compaſſe that</l>
                  <l>Which is by them, in ſecret almed at,</l>
                  <l>(Unleſſe prevented) and involve us more</l>
                  <l>In <hi>ſervile ſlaveries,</hi> then heretofore.</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:116012:39"/>
                  <l>For, doubtleſs, moſt of thoſe who did befriend</l>
                  <l>The tyranny of <hi>Kings,</hi> will to that end</l>
                  <l>Adhere to theſe, in hope by doing thus,</l>
                  <l>To be reveng'd at laſt, on <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe are no ſuch Propoſalls, as may hatch</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Cocatrice;</hi> or, be abus'd to catch</l>
                  <l>A <hi>private intereſt.</hi> No <hi>impoſtures</hi> are</l>
                  <l>Beneath a fair pretence obſcured here:</l>
                  <l>Nor doth their <hi>Author</hi> act the <hi>Mountebank</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To any end: For, he expects not thank</l>
                  <l>For ought by him deſign'd; nor, cares for more</l>
                  <l>But to diſcharge the debt upon his ſcore;</l>
                  <l>And (if occaſion be) to find a <hi>gap,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through which, without a <hi>miſchief,</hi> he may ſcape.</l>
                  <l>Which, if he do, he will confeſs, 'tis more</l>
                  <l>Then ever he could boaſt of heretofore;</l>
                  <l>Or, any other, who thus interrupted</l>
                  <l>The <hi>wilfull practiſe</hi> of a <hi>power corrupted,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unleſs that GOD, whom nothing can withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Secur'd him, by an over-ruling hand;</l>
                  <l>Or, by a miracle did change their heart,</l>
                  <l>As when he did great <hi>Nineveh</hi> convert.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is the ſum of that, which I remember</l>
                  <l>Kept me awake, ſome nights of this <hi>November,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When my <hi>affairs,</hi> which then at hazard lay,</l>
                  <l>Had tir'd in vain my body all the day;</l>
                  <l>For, my <hi>neceſſities</hi> requir'd the one,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>conſcience</hi> cry'd, the t'other muſt be done;</l>
                  <l>And, if, now ought the worſe thereby I fare,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>lot,</hi> as I am able, I will bear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Much more was repreſented to my view,</l>
                  <l>Which I am unprepar'd (as yet) to <hi>ſhew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And you to hear: but, if I had a <hi>pen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As acceptable, as ſome other men,</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:116012:39"/>
                  <l>(And undiſturb'd) it might produce perchance,</l>
                  <l>That, which the <hi>Publike weal,</hi> might much advance:</l>
                  <l>Or, had I but a volubility</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>tongue,</hi> to help my <hi>fluid</hi> memory;</l>
                  <l>Or, durſt declare my <hi>thoughts,</hi> e're them I ſee</l>
                  <l>Array'd in <hi>words,</hi> that, weigh'd they firſt might be:</l>
                  <l>Yea, could I <hi>ſpeak,</hi> as many now can do,</l>
                  <l>More in <hi>one hour,</hi> then they e're thought in <hi>two,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or, then I can be underſtood in <hi>three</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Much more eſteem'd would my <hi>Propoſalls</hi> be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here I had fixt, but, that there comes to mind</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſupplement,</hi> remaining yet behind,</l>
                  <l>Of ſomwhat repreſented, as relating</l>
                  <l>Unto this <hi>Parliaments</hi> accommodating,</l>
                  <l>With due <hi>conveniences;</hi> and with ſupply</l>
                  <l>Of things pertaining to the <hi>Majesty,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Supreme Senates:</hi> For, though, doubtleſs, they</l>
                  <l>Are beſt adorned, who themſelves array</l>
                  <l>With <hi>holineſs;</hi> though, they have moſt renown</l>
                  <l>When <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> is their Crown:</l>
                  <l>And, though the dignity of <hi>Governments,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conſiſteth not in outward <hi>ornaments,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, neat <hi>accommodations;</hi> yet, the <hi>wiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Having regard to mans infirmities,</l>
                  <l>Did in all ages, by their joynt conſents,</l>
                  <l>Add to <hi>eſſentiall things,</hi> ſuch <hi>accidents</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As might to thoſe men, make their worth appear,</l>
                  <l>Who could not ſee, what in <hi>themſelves,</hi> they were:</l>
                  <l>And, that they who diſcern'd it, might not find</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diſcouragements,</hi> in that which is <hi>injoyn'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To which end, we preſcribe unto the ſick,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>gilded pill,</hi> and trim with <hi>Rethorick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Arguments,</hi> thereby to palliate</l>
                  <l>What, we to others would inſinuate.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:116012:40"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, to this end, were tipifi'd to me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some things,</hi> which will, perhaps, hereafter be,</l>
                  <l>Mark them, if they be worth your heed: if not,</l>
                  <l>Let them be paſſed over, as forgot.</l>
                  <l>Methought, I ſaw WHITEHALL new model'd out;</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Tow'rs</hi> adorn'd, with <hi>ſtrong walls</hi> fenc'd about;</l>
                  <l>With <hi>buildings,</hi> having much <hi>variety</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Contriv'd into a neat <hi>conformity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>fair aſpect,</hi> and duly beautifi'd</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Gardens, walks,</hi> and with what els, beſide,</l>
                  <l>Did render it magnificently fit</l>
                  <l>For their abode, who did inhabit it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beſide the <hi>Fabricks,</hi> deſtined unto</l>
                  <l>Meer <hi>publike uſe,</hi> and <hi>common works</hi> to do;</l>
                  <l>As, in the <hi>Firmaments</hi> wide Orb, there are</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Twelve manſions;</hi> ſo, <hi>twelve ſtructures,</hi> ſaw I there,</l>
                  <l>In each of which (as in the <hi>Zodiake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>twelve celeſtial ſigns,</hi> their Stations take)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Senators,</hi> who <hi>moneth by moneth,</hi> vvere choſe,</l>
                  <l>Had their diſtinct abodes; each one of thoſe</l>
                  <l>In <hi>lodgings,</hi> by himſelf; yet, altogether</l>
                  <l>In one <hi>pile,</hi> vvho, in one <hi>moneth</hi> vvere ſent thither:</l>
                  <l>That, for conveniency they might be neer</l>
                  <l>On all occaſions; and, that ev'ry <hi>Shire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Might thereby find the eaſier <hi>addreſſes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, quick diſpatches in their buſineſſes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>conſtant Table,</hi> of one meal a day,</l>
                  <l>Was there prepared for a frugall pay,</l>
                  <l>That none might be compelled to ſtray forth</l>
                  <l>To places unbeſeeming men of vvorth:</l>
                  <l>And, all things pertinent to preſervation</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>health,</hi> vvith ev'ry fit accommodation,</l>
                  <l>Was there contrived, ſo, as that they might</l>
                  <l>Purſue the <hi>Publike ſervice,</hi> vvith delight.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:116012:40"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>No famliy, was licens'd there, to hoſt;</l>
                  <l>No, not a <hi>wife</hi> (except a week, at moſt,</l>
                  <l>In gueſt-wiſe) leſt the <hi>publike ſervices</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Might be diſturb'd by houſhold buſineſſes:</l>
                  <l>Or, leaſt the drudgeries, or naſtineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Occaſion'd by a numerous acceſſe</l>
                  <l>Of children, ſervants, and their viſiters,</l>
                  <l>Might ſpread diſeaſes, in infectious years:</l>
                  <l>And leſt among them, ſome, through want of grace,</l>
                  <l>Might bring an <hi>evell name</hi> upon that place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nothing uncomely, or diſorder'd there</l>
                  <l>Could I behold; no noyſes did I hear,</l>
                  <l>Or ſuch loud clamors, as have oft been heard,</l>
                  <l>Among the rude <hi>Jncommers,</hi> and the <hi>guard;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, ſuch an <hi>lawfull ſilence,</hi> as if there</l>
                  <l>The Turks <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> always preſent were</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Mutes</hi> attended. To offend the eye,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>ſmell,</hi> no <hi>dung,</hi> or <hi>ſinks,</hi> did open lye.</l>
                  <l>I ſaw not thee, a deſpicable ſhed;</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Coach hous'd</hi> there, or any <hi>Coach horſe</hi> fed:</l>
                  <l>No <hi>little children</hi> in the <hi>garden</hi> ſprawling,</l>
                  <l>Or, in the <hi>Galleries,</hi> or <hi>Chambers</hi> yawling:</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Bakers Boy</hi> went tooting of his horn:</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Milk pails</hi> there, from place to place were born,</l>
                  <l>As in thoſe <hi>Courts,</hi> and <hi>Allies</hi> which we ſee</l>
                  <l>Peſter'd with <hi>Inmates,</hi> and <hi>poor lodgers be:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor was there born <hi>through any paſſage</hi> there,</l>
                  <l>(Save ſuch, as out of <hi>common concourſe</hi> were)</l>
                  <l>Unſcemly burthens, or, ought els permitted</l>
                  <l>But what the honor of the place befitted.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Guard</hi> was needleſſe then for their defence,</l>
                  <l>(Since, <hi>juſtice, mercy,</hi> and true <hi>innocence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are <hi>guard</hi> enough, and keep more ſafe, by far,</l>
                  <l>Then if an armed <hi>Phalanx</hi> doubled were)</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:116012:41"/>
                  <l>They had true peace within; and through the land</l>
                  <l>No man againſt them, durſt to lift a <hi>hand;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, ev'ry one was ready to attend them,</l>
                  <l>And with their <hi>lives,</hi> as their <hi>life,</hi> to defend them.</l>
                  <l>Yet, for <hi>magnificency,</hi> and to further</l>
                  <l>The preſervation of <hi>reſpect</hi> and <hi>order,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In times of <hi>concourſe;</hi> and that no <hi>addreſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be made, but with all due <hi>reſpectiveneſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They had an <hi>able Band</hi> of men ſelected</l>
                  <l>Out from among thoſe perſons <hi>well-affected,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe faith and <hi>valour</hi> had been well approved</l>
                  <l>In <hi>publike ſervices;</hi> who, had unmoved</l>
                  <l>Stood firm in trialls, and whoſe converſation</l>
                  <l>Had gained them an honeſt <hi>reputation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And theſe, <hi>arm'd, govern'd, decently array'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>liveries alike,</hi> and <hi>duly paid,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Appear'd to give attendance altogether</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Princes,</hi> or <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> came thither:</l>
                  <l>And, in their <hi>turns,</hi> at other times, to do,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>ſervice,</hi> which they were injoyn'd unto.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rhen, foraſmuch, as <hi>outward habits</hi> draw</l>
                  <l>Reſpect unto mens perſons, there, I ſaw</l>
                  <l>That cuſtome, which all <hi>Senators</hi> did hold</l>
                  <l>In ſtrict obſervance, through moſt times of old,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> who repreſent</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Nation,</hi> entred not the <hi>parliament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>common habits</hi> only; but, each one</l>
                  <l>A <hi>robe.</hi> or <hi>upper garment,</hi> did put on</l>
                  <l>Peculiar to that <hi>Semate,</hi> differing neither</l>
                  <l>In <hi>faſhion, ſtuffe,</hi> or <hi>colour</hi> from each other.</l>
                  <l>To ſignifie (as I conceive) thereby</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>brother-hood,</hi> and their <hi>equality;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that, they being thereby <hi>differenced</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>vulgar perſons,</hi> might be honored</l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:116012:41"/>
                  <l>According to their <hi>place,</hi> and known among,</l>
                  <l>And by the people, as they paſt along</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Senate;</hi> or, as to and fro,</l>
                  <l>from place to place, on their affairs they go.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moreover, when that they had laid aſide</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Senate robes,</hi> about their necks I ſpi'd</l>
                  <l>A <hi>golden Wreath,</hi> which thereat pendent had</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Tablet,</hi> whereon was enamelled,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Britiſh Iſles,</hi> within the <hi>Ocean</hi> plac't;</l>
                  <l>And with a Verge of curled waves embrac't:</l>
                  <l>Which was beſtown upon them for a badge</l>
                  <l>of <hi>honor,</hi> and likewiſe to priviledge</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>perſons,</hi> whereſoe're they were unknown;</l>
                  <l>That <hi>due reſpect</hi> might ev'ry where be ſhown,</l>
                  <l>And no <hi>affronts</hi> receiv'd. Theſe <hi>badges</hi> were</l>
                  <l>From man to man, (and ſtill from year to year)</l>
                  <l>Reſign'd to their <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> to be born</l>
                  <l>By thoſe whom their <hi>Electors</hi> ſhould return.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Much more I ſaw, which ſhould I here relate,</l>
                  <l>Would yet appear, things worthy laughing at;</l>
                  <l>(As theſe declar'd, already do to ſome)</l>
                  <l>But, when the daies of their admittance come,</l>
                  <l>(Which I believe draw neer) it will be found</l>
                  <l>That theſe <hi>Previſions</hi> had ſome likely ground;</l>
                  <l>And that the <hi>heart,</hi> from whence all this did flow</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meant</hi> well to you, though theſe things prove not ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear me with patience, but a few words more,</l>
                  <l>And, to their freedome, I'le your ears reſtore.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>country folks,</hi> to keep out <hi>Witches,</hi> do</l>
                  <l>within the <hi>threſhold,</hi> nail a <hi>horſes ſhoe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So did I, at the <hi>fore-door</hi> of this <hi>piece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſert a <hi>charm,</hi> to keep out <hi>prejudice:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, now, if ſome way els, it in be brought,</l>
                  <l>That, at the <hi>Back-door,</hi> I may thruſt it out,</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:116012:42"/>
                  <l>I'le fix a <hi>Si quis,</hi> (or it may be mo)</l>
                  <l>Upon the <hi>Poſtern Gate,</hi> before I go.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If any think the <hi>poſture</hi> we are in</l>
                  <l>Will ſtill as proſperous be, as it hath been,</l>
                  <l>Or, that GOD will this <hi>Nation</hi> ſtill deliver</l>
                  <l>By <hi>miracles,</hi> although we ſhall perſever,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>high proſumptions,</hi> and <hi>ſupreme neglect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of that <hi>compliance,</hi> which he doth expect;</l>
                  <l>They greatly are deceiv'd: For, know, the end</l>
                  <l>Of moſt things, on <hi>contingence</hi> doth depend.</l>
                  <l>We of this <hi>Nation,</hi> having walk'd upon</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Y or, <hi>Ypſilon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are come unto the foot thereof, <hi>this day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where lies before our face a <hi>double way,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>one</hi> of them directeth us unto</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proſperity;</hi> the <hi>other</hi> to our <hi>woe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On this hand, <hi>Bliſs,</hi> on that hand, <hi>Curſes lie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Proceed <hi>this way,</hi> and live; <hi>go that,</hi> and <hi>die.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n <hi>Davids</hi> temp'rall Kingdom, (though there had</l>
                  <l>Large promiſes, concerning it, been made)</l>
                  <l>Was on his heirs intail'd, for their fruition,</l>
                  <l>Not abſolutely, but upon <hi>condition;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, being broken; all th' <hi>externall power</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>glory</hi> of it vaniſht; ſo ſhall our.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moreover, <hi>if that any</hi> ſhall believe</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>hazards</hi> are far leſs then I conceive;</l>
                  <l>Let them not truſt to ſuch a <hi>dream</hi> as that,</l>
                  <l>Leſt they diſcover, when it is too late,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>dangers</hi> threatning us: For, I have been</l>
                  <l>Inform'd aright, what perills we are in.</l>
                  <l>And, whereas, of thoſe things which paſſed by</l>
                  <l>From time to time, I ſought to ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>My <hi>private knowledge</hi> only, (that I might</l>
                  <l>Aſſured be I had obſerv'd aright)</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:116012:42"/>
                  <l>If I had thereby gathe'rd proofs, to ſhow</l>
                  <l>To other men, the truth of what I know,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould of ſuch things demonſtration give,</l>
                  <l>As few ſuſpect, and fewer would believe;</l>
                  <l>And you would ſee, that we are in a courſe</l>
                  <l>Like his, who in a dark night rode his horſe</l>
                  <l>O're <hi>Chepstow bridge,</hi> upon a ſingle board,</l>
                  <l>When lowd to him, the <hi>dreadfull waters</hi> roar'd,</l>
                  <l>(Beneath the broken arch) and ſeem'd to ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh fool! take heed, ther's danger in the way.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſome, perhaps, if they aſſured were</l>
                  <l>What <hi>hazzards</hi> they have paſt, would die through fear,</l>
                  <l>As it is ſaid he did, when he had ſight,</l>
                  <l>Next <hi>morn,</hi> of what he ſcaped <hi>over-night.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We think perhaps, we all this while have been</l>
                  <l>Upon as plain firm ground as <hi>Richmond-green,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or in a <hi>Courſe,</hi> wherein as ſafe we run</l>
                  <l>As on the race at <hi>Bauſted-downs</hi> at noon;</l>
                  <l>When we are rather dancing o're the tops</l>
                  <l>Of tottering <hi>pinacles,</hi> on <hi>rotten roper,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where, but that we by providence are kept,</l>
                  <l>We down had fell, at every Stride we ſtept.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, for the moſt part, every <hi>loſſe</hi> and <hi>ſtreight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which we are in, makes us but lay more weight</l>
                  <l>Upon the weak; and each <hi>Deliverance</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth but increaſe our <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>arrogance.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As if we were reſolved, without heed</l>
                  <l>of <hi>judgments,</hi> or of <hi>mercies,</hi> to proceed,</l>
                  <l>Untill <hi>confuſion</hi> ſhould compell us to</l>
                  <l>What we might <hi>orderly,</hi> and <hi>timely</hi> do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Laſtly, <hi>if any</hi> ſhall be pleas'd to ſay,</l>
                  <l>Or dream (as peradventure many may)</l>
                  <l>That, with <hi>affairs</hi> I intermeddle here</l>
                  <l>Which pertinent to my <hi>Superiors</hi> are,</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:116012:43"/>
                  <l>And not to me: To all theſe <hi>be it known,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>buſineſſe</hi> which I treat of is mine <hi>own.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I claim, in this <hi>Republike,</hi> with the beſt,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſhare,</hi> proportion'd to my <hi>interest;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>freedome,</hi> boldly to expreſſe my mind</l>
                  <l>As often as I juſt occaſion find.</l>
                  <l>the <hi>common liberty,</hi> and <hi>common peace</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are truly <hi>mine,</hi> and no mans, more, or leſs:</l>
                  <l>I <hi>fought</hi> for't, and I <hi>pay</hi> for't, thrice my <hi>ſhare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>According to the <hi>part,</hi> which many beare.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Countries</hi> wrong is <hi>mine;</hi> her grief my ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>And therefore they that wound her thruſt me thorow.</l>
                  <l>They, who her <hi>wealth</hi> or <hi>honor</hi> fool away,</l>
                  <l>Fool me, when in that kind the fools they play:</l>
                  <l>And, therefore they, who thereto <hi>Traytors</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>Are therein alſo <hi>Traytors</hi> unto me;</l>
                  <l>And no man can without apparent wrong</l>
                  <l>Reſtraint impoſe upon my <hi>pen,</hi> or <hi>tongue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In pleading of her <hi>cauſe;</hi> nor will I fear</l>
                  <l>To act my <hi>own work</hi> in my proper <hi>ſphere.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, though I have not power to make a <hi>Law,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or raiſe an <hi>Armie</hi> which can keep in awe</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>private enemies,</hi> and <hi>open foes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, I have <hi>charms</hi> equivalent to thoſe,</l>
                  <l>In ſome reſpects; which operate unſeen</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>ends,</hi> whereto they have intended been;</l>
                  <l>And will have due <hi>effects,</hi> in their deſpight</l>
                  <l>Who ſeek to trample on the <hi>common Right.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this aſſurance, here I'le add a cloſe,</l>
                  <l>To this, and leave th'event to GOD'S diſpoſe;</l>
                  <l>Who, if we ſhall neglect (a few weeks more)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Good counſell,</hi> as we have done heretofore,</l>
                  <l>Will break down that, which might preſerv'd have bin,</l>
                  <l>And, on another <hi>Baſe</hi> his <hi>work</hi> begin.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 30.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
